<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to a lady furnishing her with Scripture testimonies against the principal points and doctrines of popery</title>
            <author>Barecroft, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30916</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B757</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20623</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12224778</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12224778</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56476</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30916)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56476)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 621:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to a lady furnishing her with Scripture testimonies against the principal points and doctrines of popery</title>
                  <author>Barecroft, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>83 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56476:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56476:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER TO A LADY, Furniſhing her with <hi>Scripture Teſtimonies</hi> Againſt the Principal Points and Doctrines OF POPERY.</p>
            <q>All Scripture is given by Inſpiration of God, and is Profitable for Reproof, for Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, for Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs: That the Man of God may be Perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all Good Works,
<bibl>2 Tim. 3. 16, 17.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>The Law of the Lord is Perfect, converting the Soul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <bibl>Pſal. 19. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Search the Scriptures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <bibl>John 5. 39.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Bleſſed is he that readeth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <bibl>Rev. 1. 3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed,</hi> July 6. 1688.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Taylor,</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in <hi>St. Paul's Church-Yard,</hi> M DC LXXX VIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:56476:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56476:2"/>
            <head>Admonition to the Reader, concerning the Authority and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Holy Scriptures.</head>
            <p>THe following Papers, being intended only for a private Satisfaction, and not for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick View, are writ in a Stile agreeable to the Sex to which they are dedicated, and the few Arguments here and there added, either to explain or Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate a Text of Scripture, are ſuch as are more obvious to a Female Capacity, than perhaps the common way of Arguing uſed by one great Diſputant againſt another is. For it was no more my intent, than it was my Buſineſs, in writing to Women; who by Reaſon of their general want of Learning, underſtand nothing of Logical Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, and as little of Syllogiſmal Inferences, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make a thing plain, by rendring it more unintel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible: But to make every thing as obvious and plain to the moſt ordinary Underſtanding, as I might, tho' my Words were never ſo homely; And though it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, The Lady to whom theſe Papers were eſpecially directed, is a Perſon endued with better Parts, and more Learning than others of her Sex generally are; yet I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, That many more of her Society or Acquaintance, might be concerned in the Reading of them: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thought, as a plain Method would not be unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56476:3"/> to the Lady her ſelf, ſo it would certainly be both more Acceptable and Profitable to others, not loaden with ſo much Sagacity and Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>But, ſince in this Undertaking I have wholly relyed on the Teſtimony of the Scriptures, and have drawn all my Arguments from them; I think it proper to vindicate my Proceeding that way, by giving the Reader a curſory Account of the Supreme Authority of the Sacred Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, conſiſting in two Particulars: The Firſt is, Their containing, fully, all things needful for our Salvation. And the Second, Their being ſufficient to determine Points of Doubt and Controverſie. In both which I ſhall ſtill make my Appeal to the Scriptures themſelves; and likewiſe intermix a few Teſtimones of the Fathers, not for Confirmation of the Scriptures Authority, for that is evident enough in it ſelf; but to ſhew the Opinion of thoſe great Pillars of the Church in a Matter, about which there is ſo great a Diſagreement betwixt us and the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin therefore with the firſt Evidence of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority of the Scriptures; Their containing, fully, all things needful for our Salvation.</p>
            <p>The Evangeliſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. 30. tells us, <hi>That Jeſus did many ſigns, in the preſence of his diſciples, which are not written in this book. But theſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>are written, That ye might believe that Jeſus is the Chriſt, the ſon of God, and that believing ye might have life through his name.</hi> 
               <q>And <note place="margin">Cyril. in Praef. in Johan.</note> this Goſpel by S. <hi>John,</hi> may without Injury, be thought to excel the other three, ſays S. <hi>Cyril;</hi>
               </q> and he gives no weak Reaſons for it: One of which is, <q>That it contains all things pertaining to Truth, which the other do alſo, but not in ſo high a Strain: For whereas the reſt do moſt Exquiſitely deſcribe the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogy of our Saviour, either deſcending from <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> or aſcending from <hi>Joſeph</hi> to <hi>Adam;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56476:3"/> S. John</hi> has not much laboured in theſe Matters, but with an aſpiring Mind ſeems to ſoar beyond Human Poſſibility, and is not afraid, in expreſs Words to ſet down his Ineffable Generation; <hi>In the beginning was the word, and the word was with God, and the word was God. The ſame was in the beginning with God:</hi> And ſo aſpires directly to the Foundation of Divine Truth.</q> Where, by the way, it will not be amiſs to obſerve, That this Evangeliſt was the beloved Diſciple of our Lord, and therefore it cannot reaſonably be ſuppoſed he would conceal any thing from him that was neceſſary to be known: But on the contrary, he revealed more to him than was needful to be ſet down, in ſome Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars whereof he was commanded to be Silent; as may be ſeen, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10. 4. But when any thing might be known, he is to declare it, Chap. 22. 10. and Chap. 1. 3. <hi>They are bleſſed who read and hear the words of this prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, with an intent to keep thoſe things which are written therein.</hi> So then, though we are ignorant of ſome things, yet by what is written, we may ſufficiently be acquainted with whatever is neceſſary for us to know.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 20. after he had told the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> Verſe 30, That <hi>of their own ſelves ſhould ariſe men, ſpeaking per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe things to draw away diſciples after them.</hi> At the 32 Verſe he commends them to God, and to the Word of his Grace, <hi>which,</hi> he tells them, <hi>is able to build them up, and to give them an inheritance among all them which are ſanctified.</hi> And leſt it ſhould be thought that he had broached ſome unwritten Traditions of his own, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes Chap. 26. 22. That <hi>having obtained help of God,</hi> he <hi>ſtill continued, witneſſing both to ſmall and great, but ſaying no other things than thoſe which the Prophets and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes did ſay ſhould come.</hi> Accordingly he tells the <hi>Romans,</hi> in his Epiſtle to them, Chap. 1. 16. That he <hi>was not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the goſpel of Chriſt, becauſe it is the power of God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56476:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> unto ſalvation, to every one that believeth.</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. 4. <hi>Whatſoever things were written aforetime, were written for our learning, that we through Patience and comfort of the Scriptures might have hope.</hi> And ſays S. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> 
               <q>Wherefore are theſe things written, but that we ſhould <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Rom. hom.</hi> 9. <hi>In</hi> 2 <hi>Cor. hom.</hi> 13. <hi>In ſynop. Athan.</hi>
                  </note> learn them? For ſays he, The Scriptures are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of all, the moſt exact Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, Guide and Rule.</q> And according to S. <hi>Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The Anchors and Support of our Faith. And <hi>Irenaeus</hi> calls them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the immoveable Canon of Truth; and the Pillar and Foundation of our Faith. And we being ſure of what the Apoſtle ſays, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16, 17. <hi>That all Scripture is given by Inſpiration of God, and is profitable for doctrin, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſs, That the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Canonem fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetarum &amp; Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris figi atque ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minari. Aug de C. D. l.</hi> 11. <hi>c. 41.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>all good Works;</hi> may ſafely conclude with S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> That the Rule of Faith is fixed and terminated in the Books of the Prophets and Apoſtles. It was the conſtant Opinion of this great Doctor of the Gentiles, That the Scriptures were of themſelves able to make Men Wiſe unto Salvation. Neither is he alone; for St. <hi>James</hi> aſſures us, That they are able to ſave our Souls, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 21. And therefore St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls 'em a more ſure word of Prophecy, than a Voice from Heaven; and ſays, That all Men would do well that they take good heed to 'em, as unto a Light that ſhineth in a dark place, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19. And our Lord himſelf, in the Parable, brings in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> telling the Rich Man in Hell, That his Brethren had <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, whom let 'em hear, ſays he; for if they will not hear them, neither will they be perſuaded, though one roſe from the Dead, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 29. 31. Upon which words, St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence was, <q>That we ſhould believe the Scriptures. Though the Dead ſhould riſe, and though Angels
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56476:4"/> ſhould deſcend from Heaven, we muſt prefer the Teſtimony of Scriptures before them: According to the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 8.</q> 
               <hi>Though we, or an Angel from Heaven, preach any other Goſpel unto you, than that which we have preached unto you, let him be accurſed.</hi> All which I take to be Indications plain enough of the ſufficiency of the Scriptures, as to all things pertaining to Salvation.</p>
            <p>But beſides this, I ſaid they were alſo in themſelves ſufficient to determin Points of Controverſie.</p>
            <p>The Pſalmiſt ſays of the Word of God, That it is a Lamp to his Feet, and a Light to his Path, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 105. And therefore it was that he ſo often ſpeaks of ordering himſelf according to this Word, and prays ſo earneſtly to God to enable him to do it.</p>
            <p>And thus the Prophet expoſtulates with the Jews, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 19, 20. <hi>When they ſhall ſay unto you, Seek unto them which have familiar ſpirits, and unto wizards that peep and mutter; Should not a people ſeek unto their God? for the living, to the dead? To the law and to the teſtimony: if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the way of the Apoſtles, on all occaſions, to have recourſe to the Scriptures. Thus St. <hi>Peter,</hi> in his Sermon to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> to confirm his Doctrin of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> ſays, <hi>To him give all the Prophets witneſs, that through his Name whoſoever believeth on him, ſhall receive remiſſion of ſins,</hi> Act. 10. 43. And that it was the conſtant practice of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> no Man can deny that has had the leaſt converſe with his Writings; eſpecially that great Axiom of his, which has never been contradicted, That the Scriptures are given by Inſpiration of God, and are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for Doctrin, for Reproof, for Correction, for Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs, is a more than ordinary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his Opinion in this particular. And as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, was the only refuge of thoſe Primitive Builders of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56476:5"/> the Church. And it was the very ſame method that our Lord himſelf took to reprove the Tempter, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. 4. <hi>It is written, Man ſhall not live by bread alone,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>It is written, Thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God.</hi> And <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>It is written, Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God.</hi> And thus he us'd always to bring the Teſtimonies of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets againſt the impious Objections of the Jews; very often telling them, That he did not ſpeak his own Words, but the Word of him that ſent him; that is, the Word of God.</p>
            <p>And now, would it not be a thing to be wonder'd at, if the Holy Fathers of the Church ſhould be ignorant of this way of arguing? Or if they did know it, that they would not chuſe to follow his Example whom they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to worſhip and obey? But we have no cauſe to wonder at this, but rather at their ignorance, or wilful ſtubbornneſs, who pretend to be acquainted with them, and yet, ſeemingly at leaſt, aſſert their Sentiments and Practice in this matter, to be contrary to their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors.</p>
            <p>It was uſual with <hi>Baſil</hi> thus to expreſs himſel, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Euſtath. 80</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Let the Scriptures, which are divinely inſpir'd, be Judge between us.</hi> For, ſays he, <hi>Whatſoever</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem Etb. Defin.</hi> 80. <hi>c. 22. 6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>is contrary to them, is not of Faith, and therefore ſinful.</hi> Every Word or Cauſe ought to be tried and confirm'd by the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Neither does St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> come behind him in this <note place="margin">Cypr. ad Pomp. cont. Steph. Pap.</note> particular; <q>If (ſays he) the Pipes through which Water is conveyed into the City, ſhould be ſuddenly deficient, ſhould we not go preſently to the Spring, that thence we may know the cauſe of the defect, whether the Spring it ſelf is dry, or whether the Pipes are ſtopt by any thing which may hinder the courſe of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? And ſo the Pipes being clear'd, the City may be ſupplied with Water as before. So ought the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56476:5"/> of the Goſpel to do: In matters of Doubt they ſhould go to our Lord and his Apoſtles, that they may model their Actions by their Doctrin, as the Fountain and Original of Divine Truth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> likewiſe would accept of no Argument that was not drawn from the Scriptures. And by this <note place="margin">Tertul. de carne Chriſt. Idem de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. mort.</note> he confuted the Hereticks of his time. <q>For (ſays he) take away the Sophiſtry of the Heathen Philoſophers, which the Hereticks make uſe of, and when they come to argue from the Scriptures they will not be able to ſtand.</q>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſays, That if any thing is aſſerted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the authority of the Scriptures to back it on, it leaves <note place="margin">Chryſ. in Pſalm 95.</note> the Hearers in doubt. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſays <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus; We ſay nothing againſt the Scriptures.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cl. Al. de Pet. Strom. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Theod. dial.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Id. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap. 3.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Theodoret,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>I confide in the Scriptures only.</hi> To which we may add his Teſtimony of the Saying of <hi>Conſtantine the Great,</hi> 
               <q>That the Books of the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles, and the Oracles of the the ancient Prophets do evidently teach us, what we are to think of the Divine Power. Therefore in every ſeditious Controverſie, let us diſcuſs the Point in queſtion, by the Teſtimony of thoſe divinely inſpir'd Writings. Whence we may ſee, that all the Fathers are not againſt us in this matter.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I think <hi>Origen</hi> may come in for one on our ſide. For in his Comment upon the Sixteenth Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> having explained thoſe Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Apoſtle, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17, 18. and coming to <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. where the Apoſtle tells the <hi>Romans,</hi> That their Obedience is come abroad unto all Men: And that he is therefore glad on their behalf, <q>The Apoſtle (ſays he) therefore rejoyces over thoſe that were obedient, being ſure that as he had taught them not to uſe that general Obedience which they indifferently pay to all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56476:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> Men, for that which is due to God only, whereby they obey God rather than Man; ſo this Obedience was embraced by them before the other. For 'tis indeed an argument of no little diſcretion, but of a quick and moſt piercing Judgment, if we can diſcern what Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is to be followed, and what is rather to be reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. In a word, our Lord himſelf in the Goſpel ſays, <hi>Beware of them which come to you in ſheeps cloathing, but inwardly are devouring wolves.</hi> Therefore a watchful Soul and ſetled Mind are required in order to our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcovering the plain ſimplicity of Sheep, or the more hidden malice and greedineſs of Wolves. Whence we may learn what great danger they are in, who neglect the ſtudy of the Holy Scriptures, from which only they can be furniſhed with ſuch a knowledge and diſcretion.</q>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> has an Expreſſion, which makes a great bluſter in the World; <q>I would not believe the Goſpel (ſays he) if the Authority of the Catholick Church did not move me to it.</q> Upon this the Authority of the Church is magnified above the Authority of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>But if St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> did not intend any ſuch thing, where are we then? He expreſs'd himſelf once to this purpoſe, <q>Thou, O God, haſt aſſur'd me, that not they who <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. Conf. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c. 5.</hi>
                  </note> believ'd thy Books, which with ſo great Authority thou haſt eſtabliſh'd in almoſt all the World; but they who did not, were culpable: Neither are they to be heard, who ſhall ask me, how I know, that thoſe Books are given to Men by the Spirit of One moſt true God.</q> Which ſhews, that he did not altogether rely on the Teſtimony of the Church, which was only out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; but chiefly the inward Witneſs of the Holy Ghoſt in his Conſcience. But we may know more of his Mind by more of his Words; <q>We (ſays he) do
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56476:6"/> not bring a falſe Ballance, that we may make things <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Idem. cont. Donat. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c. 6.</hi>
                  </note> weigh what we pleaſe, and how we pleaſe, and ſo give judgment what is light, and what heavy: But we give you the divine Ballance of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Treaſures of the Lord, and by that we tell you what is heavy; yet not we, but the Lord himſelf; who having weighed all things already, we tell you from him what is heavy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> And can we think that Great Father ever intended to ſet up the Authority of the Church above the Scriptures? He does not ſay, We tell you from the Church what is light, and what heavy; but, we tell you from the Scriptures. And thus again, <q>There are (ſays he) certain Books of the <note place="margin">Id. de unit. Eccl. c. 3.</note> Lord, to whoſe Authority we wholly aſſent, which we firmly believe, and in all things obey. In them let us ſeek the Church, by them let us diſcuſs our Cauſe.</q> Now, if St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> did really believe the Scriptures, on no other account than barely the Churches Teſtimony, why does he ſay, He muſt find the Church in the Scriptures? This would be to run round in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determinate circle; firſt to look for the Church in the Scriptures, and then to ſearch for the Scriptures in the Church. I don't ſee how theſe can ſtand together. But let it be as it will, we may with more ſafety give credit to what a Man is conſtant in, than to what he ſays but once, or, it may be, never at all; and ſo we may aſſure our ſelves of the conceſſion of this Holy Father to what we aſſert, That the Scriptures are the ſupreme Decider of Controverſies. The only thing needful to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to what has been already produc'd, is, That nothing ought to be put to, or taken from the Word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellarmin</hi> acknowledges the Scriptures to be a Rule, but ſays 'tis only partly ſo; for the Scriptures joyn'd with Traditions, make one perfect Rule.</p>
            <p>But we have ſeen that the Scriptures alone are a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56476:7"/> Rule; and, <q>An Infallible Rule (ſays St. <hi>Baſil</hi>) ought to be ſo, without addition or diminution. And <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil. cont. Eunom. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Id. Conf. Fid.</hi>
                  </note> further, That it is a manifeſt departing from the Faith, and an evidence of Pride, either to take away any thing from what is written, or to add any thing that is not written; for our Lord has ſaid, <hi>My ſheep hear my voice.</hi>
               </q> 
               <q>And (ſays St. <hi>Jerom</hi>) Whatever does not come from the <note place="margin">Jerom. in Matth. 23.</note> Holy Scriptures, is as eaſily condemn'd as approv'd.</q> 
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us, <q>That after the Death of the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. Hiſt l.</hi> 3. <hi>c. 32.</hi>
                  </note> Apoſtles, though the Scriptures were extant, yet the Church did not long continue an unſpotted Virgin, but Hereſies and Corruptions of the Goſpel encreaſed apace.</q> And then I would fain know what method the Orthodox Doctors took to purge and refine the Church again? I ſuppoſe it may be anſwer'd, that, A General Council was to repreſent the whole Church, and to determine the Points in Controverſie. Granting this, the next Queſtion will be, which way the Doctors aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Council proceeded in this great Affair? Did they appeal to the Church? The moſt impious Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks would confidently affirm, That only they were of the True Church. Wou'd they appeal to the Fathers? There were many Learned Men who in their Writings maintain'd the worſt of Hereſies. Wou'd they appeal to Apoſtolical Traditions? The Founders of many of the greateſt Hereſies, lived in the Times of the Apoſtles; and on that ſcore, had as good a plea for their knowing their Sentiments, as any of the Orthodox Fathers could have. I am certain the firſt <hi>Nicene</hi> Council took no ſuch way, but on all occaſions urg'd the Scriptures againſt the Opinions of thoſe Hereticks they were to deal with, as might be ſhewn at large, if it was abſolutely neceſſary to our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>At preſent let us content our ſelves with a few Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of the Fathers againſt ſuch proceedings.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:56476:7"/>
            <p>And firſt, againſt Appealing to the Churches Cuſtome; St <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſays, <q>a Cuſtome which ſome have taken up, <note place="margin">Cypr. ad Pomp. cont. Steph. Pap.</note> ought not to prevail againſt the Truth; for Cuſtome without the Truth, is but the Ornament of an Error: For which Reaſon let us forſake the Error of ſuch a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and follow the Truth.</q> And when S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> bids us ſeek the Church in the Scriptures; he cannot intend, in my Opinion, That we ſhould follow the Church in any thing repugnant to the Scriptures: But beſides, A Rule of Faith ought to be Perfect. <q>But <hi>Origen</hi> tells us, That as <note place="margin">Orig. in Ezech. hom. 1.</note> on every Floor there is Chaff as well as Wheat, ſo is the Church on Earth, ſome part Wheat, and the reſt Chaff.</q> And upon <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 14. where it is ſaid, <note place="margin">Id. in Matth. hom. 15.</note> That <hi>the blind and the lame came into the Temple to Chriſt, and he healed them:</hi> 
               <q>The Moral Conſtruction of this, ſays he, is, That in the Church all cannot ſee, neither can all walk Upright; but ſome are Blind and others Lame. To which he immediately applies this Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as the moſt effectual: They, ſays he, who are ſenſible of their own Blindneſs, ſince there is no other way to be rid of it, but by the Word of God, they ſhould apply themſelves to that, and they cannot miſs of a Cure. Which is enough to prove the Inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Churches Cuſtomes or Authority, as to Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith at leaſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Neither will the Teſtimonies of the Fathers be of any Force in this Particular: For a Rule of Faith muſt be full of Knowledge, and ſufficiently able to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us. But what ſays S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> of himſelf? <q>I am <note place="margin">Aug. ep. 119.</note> not only ignorant, ſays he, in many other Things, but even in the Holy Scriptures themſelves, I am yet to learn more than I know already. And thus he elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where <note place="margin">Ep. ad Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> expreſſes himſelf: To the Books of the Scriptures only, which are called Canonical, do I owe this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that I firmly believe, That none of their Pen-Men
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56476:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> have err'd in any thing they have written. But I eſteem other Writers according to their Sanctity and Learning: I do not think any thing true, meerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was their Opinion.</q> Which very well agrees with that Axiom of <hi>Tertullian;</hi> 
               <q>If, ſays he, a Biſhop, <note place="margin">Tertul. de praeſcr. haeret.</note> or Deacon, if a Widow or Maid, if a Doctor, or even a Martyr ſhould err from the Rule, would the Error be e'r the Truer or Better for their Sakes? We do not prove the Faith by the Perſons, but the Perſons by the Faith.</q> And the Acknowledgment of <hi>Biel</hi> is to the <note place="margin">Bie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſup. Can. Miſſ. l. 41.</note> ſame purpoſe; <q>That the Authority of the Fathers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pells no Man to aſſent to their Sayings, unleſs they build on the Holy Scriptures, or Divine Revelation.</q> On this account therefore S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> might well cry out, <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. 57.</note> 
               <q>Let our Writings be withdrawn, that the Book of God may be introduced.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And as for Apoſtolical Traditions, let the Teſtimony <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c. 1.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſerve for all: <q>By the Apoſtles, ſays he, the Goſpel came down to us, which they then preached; and afterward by the Will of God, they delivered to us in the Scriptures, what was to be the future Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and Pillar of our Faith.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now, if neither the Cuſtomes of the Church, nor the Judgment of the Fathers, nor Tradition, can be a perfect Rule of Faith; no more can all theſe united in a General Council be ſo: For a Rule muſt be in every reſpect perfect. But we have ſeen, That the Church is in many reſpects Defective, and the Fathers ſubject to Ignorance and Error: And if <hi>Irenaeus</hi> may be credited, The Apoſtles preached nothing contrary to what they have left us in Writing, and therefore there can be no Place for Apoſtolical Traditions. So that a Rule, which is Imperfect, and Defective in every Part, muſt needs be ſo in the whole. And <hi>Bellarmin</hi> himſelf has proved, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm. de Concil. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c. 12.</hi>
               </note> That the Decrees of General Councils cannot be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56476:8"/> Rule, becauſe they cannot pretend to immediate Divine Revelation; That they may Err in ſome things, and in many of their Definitions, they conclude only Probably. But a Rule of Faith ought to be every way Perfect, and to conclude neceſſarily. And ſuch an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Perfect Rule the Scriptures appear to be, not only from their own Teſtimony, but from Teſtimonies of the greateſt Pillars of the Church, in the Second, Third, Fourth and Fifth Centuries. And therefore if any Man's Intereſt has led him to a contrary Judgment in the later Ages of the Church, his Opinions ought not to be ſet up as a Standard againſt Antiquity joyn'd with Truth. From hence, then, we may infer, what has been already aſſerted, That the Scriptures being of themſelves a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and Un-erring Rule, nothing muſt be put to, or taken from them. To which purpoſe, beſides what has been produced already, the Reader may give himſelf the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Peruſing the following Texts; <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 32. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1. 7. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 8. and 3. 15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 18, 19. And let him learn the Danger of Adding or Tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away, that is, Doing any thing contrary to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. From theſe <hi>Lev.</hi> 10. 2. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1. 12, 13, 14, and 66. 3. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9. 15. <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. 6, 9. <hi>Mark</hi> 7. 9. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 10. From all which Texts, will evidently appear the Invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of any thing that is not built upon the true Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the danger of being led away by ſuch Vanities. And ſo I hope, I have ſufficiently vindicated my Rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on the Teſtimony of the Scriptures in the Buſineſs of the following Undertaking.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only trouble the Reader with two or three ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Cautions, concerning the right Uſe and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of thoſe Sacred Writings, and then give him his Liberty to proceed.</p>
            <p>I. If any Man will make choice of the Scriptures for his Guide in matters that concern his Well-being here
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56476:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> and hereafter, he muſt have a care of believing every Spirit. We muſt not take things of ſuch Moment on Truſt, meerly becauſe they are aſſerted by one that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to great Learning or Inſpiration; for we are to look on the Gentlemen of theſe Times, as ſuch as will make the beſt they can of every Word, when they meet with one of an ordinary Capacity.</p>
            <p>Therefore, II. It behoveth every Man that hath any regard to his own Safety, to ſearch into theſe things him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; to read the Holy Scriptures diligently, that ſo he may learn from them whether ſuch things are true or no.</p>
            <p>But as I am now Writing to thoſe of the meaneſt Rank, in Learning lat eaſt It is neceſſary that I caution ſuch Readers of the Scriptures, againſt laying too much ſtreſs on the literal Interpretation of a Text: For the Holy Ghoſt very often makes uſe of Metaphors and other Obſcurities, wherein the Senſe is not obvious to every Eye: And tho', as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays, <hi>There is nothing ſo obſcure in one Place which in another is not made plain:</hi> Yet it is not ſuppoſed that an ordinary Reader knows how to find that Place out, or if he does, that he has Judgment enough to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie himſelf. For the Scriptures conſiſt of a Soul and a Body: The Body is the Letter, and the Soul is the true Interpretation. <hi>Every Man, therefore,</hi> ſays <hi>Origen, that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De princip. lib. 4.</note> 
               <hi>deſires to come to the Knowledge of the Truth, muſt have his Eye on every Word, for every Nation has a different way of ſpeaking; let him therefore mind rather what is ſignified, than with what Words it is expreſſed. For there are ſome things, which no Human Words can explain, but they are only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable in an honeſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding. By which Rule alſo we come to the Knowledge and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of the Holy Scriptures, that what we read is not to be underſtood accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Letter, but according to the Divinity of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit which inſpired it.</hi> Wherefore the Honeſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will do well to take care, That he is not drawn by
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56476:9"/> the Letter out of the right way. And to this end the beſt advice I can give him, is, Before he preſumes to read, to beg the Aſiſtance of God's Holy Spirit to direct and enlighten his Underſtanding. And when he meets with an obſcure Text, let him pray again, and beſides that, communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate his Doubt to ſome learned Miniſter, of whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity he is in ſome learned Miniſter, of whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity he is in ſome Meaſure aſſured, and by theſe means he may be fully ſatisfied. And thus he will ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf an humble Enquirer, and manifeſt to the World, That his Proceedings are from a Principle of Honeſty, that he ſearches only for a right Information; and on theſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts he has a Right to that encouraging Precognition of S. <hi>Cyril,</hi> in his Preface to his Comments on S. <hi>John</hi>'s Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel: <hi>The Doctrin of all the Evangeliſts,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is moſt excellent, and of Divine Extraction: For as it overlooks all things, as it were from the top of a high Tower: It ſo am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply accommodates it ſelf to all that follow it, that whoever thirſts after Divine Truth (if with an honeſt Mind, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires into the Senſe of the Scriptures) he may eaſily meet with whatever concerns him. But this gracious Satisfaction is not conferred on thoſe, who make a raſh Search, and are rather led by Human Reaſons than the Authority of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, (foraſmuch as the Holy Ghoſt does not dwell with a depraved Soul, nor does he throw his precious Jewels before Swine, to be trodden under foot) but pours out his Truth into the Hearts of all Religious Searchers after it, who not affecting Cavils and Diſputes, purſue the ready Road to the Kingdom, in ſincerity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, <hi>That true Meat and Drink which we have from the Word of God,</hi> ſays S. <hi>Jerome, is the true Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hier. in Eccl. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>of the Scriptures.</hi> And all Men having the greateſt Encouragement imaginable to read thoſe Holy Writings, if they read them to good Purpoſes, and not to wreſt them to their own Ends; let us go to that Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Divine Truth, from whence the meaneſt Reader
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56476:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> may learn whatever is neceſſary for him to know. For, ſays the Royal Pſalmiſt, <hi>The law of the Lord is perfect, converting the ſoul, the teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, making wiſe the ſimple. The ſtatutes of the Lord are right, rejoycing the Heart: The commandment of the Lord is pure, enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tening the eyes. The fear of the Lord is clean, enduring for ever: The judgments of the Lord are true and righteous al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together; more to be deſired are they than gold, yea, than much fine gold, ſweeter alſo than honey, and the honey-comb. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, by them are his Servants warned; and in keeping of them there is great reward,</hi> Pſal. 19. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. And our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour himſelf, bids us <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> Joh. 5. 39. I ſhall conclude therefore with that Pathetick Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation of S. <hi>Chryſoſtome; That all Men would read the Scriptures, and that not curſorily, but with the greateſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſ. in Col.</hi> 3. <hi>hom. 9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that they would get them Bibles as Phyſick for their Souls: And if they will not read the whole, let them turn to the New Teſtament, and read the Goſpels, Acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Epiſtles, thoſe excellent Teachers: If any Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance befall us, come hither as to a Store-houſe full of wholeſome Remedies; hence take Relief and Comfort in all Afflictions, whether loſs of Goods, or Friends, or Life it ſelf; let them not only read once, but turn over theſe Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings again and again, and faſten what they read to their Minds, that they may be ſure to remember it: For this is the Cauſe of all Evils, That Men are ignorant in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. If we go to War without Weapons, how can we be Safe? Men that are armed may overcome, at leaſt in a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to ſecure themſelves; but thoſe who are unarmed muſt fall. Therefore do not lay all the Burthen upon the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Shoulders; be Sheep, but not as Creatures void of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but as Men that know ſomething,</hi> &amp;c. And as many <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 16.</note> as walk according to this Rule, Peace be on them, and Mercy, and upon the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:56476:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Letter to a Lady,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Tenderneſs of the Female Sex renders it more obnoxious to the Sophiſtry of the Times; and the deſire of Information in Matters of Religion, may make them the more earneſt in reading the Pieces ſent abroad in the preſent Controverſie. And I preſume I need not tell you of the ſubtilty of ſome Men, who to make their Proceedings the more effectual, direct their Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions eſpecially to thoſe they think are leaſt able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them: Your own Experience, I ſuppoſe, may be Evidence ſufficient as to this Particular.</p>
            <p>There are a ſort of Men in the World who live by their Wits, and will neglect no opportunity to inſinuate ſtrange fancies into the Minds of the weaker ſort of People, to make them believe a thing is White, upon no other ground than becauſe it is not Black, though it may be Crimſon in grain. <hi>Of this ſort are they</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 6.) <hi>who creep into houſes, and lead captive ſilly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> &amp;c. And he would have us know, <hi>That in the laſt days,</hi> by means of theſe Men, <hi>perilous times ſhall come.</hi> The whole Prophecy is interpreted of the Jeſuites, by Men of Learning in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as you may ſee at large in a little Book (call'd <hi>The Moral Practice of the Jeſuites</hi>) publiſh'd by the Doctors of the <hi>Sorbon.</hi> And theſe Men have Impudence enough to intrude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Ladies Cloſets, and venturing on their good nature, to uſe their skill and ſophiſtical endeavours to cajole them into a decoy. They'll Reform the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in a quarter of an hour, and wipe off all Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56476:11"/> of Error, while one may ſay, <hi>What's this?</hi> if you'll believe their Stories. They'll tell you that the things which have ſo often been prov'd againſt that Church, are all Lies: That no ſuch Errors are embrac'd by her; but that the Church of <hi>England,</hi> if their bold Aſſertions will do the buſineſs, has only been guilty; and if She had not given her Sons Learning enough to defend her Innocence, their Forgeries muſt have paſt for current. But I hope, Madam, you know the Church of <hi>England</hi> better, than to give credit to every mouth that is open againſt Her. And I know you have a diſcerning faculty, beyond many of your Sex, whereby to judge of Opinions, right and wrong. However, give me leave to preſent you with a ſmall parcel of <hi>Scripture Teſtimonies</hi> againſt ſome of the Principal Errors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: I ſay <hi>Scripture Teſtimonies,</hi> becauſe though there are many excellent Pieces publiſh'd by our Learned Divines, yet they are too full of Learning for moſt Female capacities, and the Treatiſes large on every Subject; when, as I think the Scriptures the Supreme Judge in Matters of Religion, ſo I ſuppoſe a ſhort Catalogue of Texts from thence, directly oppoſite to ſuch Tenets as we juſtly charge upon the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and by that means a Refutation of moſt of thoſe Tenets in one ſhort Eſſay, will be more profitable, as I hope it will be more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to an ordinary Underſtanding. So that upon this account, as you will hereby, with more eaſe, be furniſh'd with what you may be ſure is true, being drawn from the Fountain of Truth, you will, I hope, be the more eaſily induc'd to pardon my Undertaking, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning nothing but Honeſty.</p>
            <p>I have choſen this way of Writing to you, Madam, Firſt, becauſe I know you delight in converſing with the Holy Writings, and ſo I ſhall be more conformable to your Inclinations. And Secondly, though I reverence
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56476:11"/> the Judgment of the Fathers, of the Church, and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils duly aſſembled, and not ſway'd by popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Inſolence; yet, as I once objected to one by word of mouth, without receiving a ſatisfactory Anſwer, The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſays, That <hi>we</hi> have Falſe Copies of the Fathers; and we anſwer, That <hi>they</hi> have corrupted the True; ſo that one of us muſt needs be in the wrong: And how ſhall we be ſatisfied in this, without compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them to the Teſtimonies of the Scriptures? And as for General Councils, they have, of late, been purg'd, or rather perverted by the Over-ruling Power of Popes and their Popular Factions, inſomuch, that when they began to act againſt the Intereſt of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> though never ſo juſtly, they were no longer allowed the liberty due to General Councils: And then what dependence can we have from them? And Laſtly, the Infallibility of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> can be no better a Decider of Controverſies, than the other two, becauſe that muſt be prov'd, if poſſible, from the Scriptures. So that, when all other Inſtruments have been tried, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures will prove the only Infallible Touch ſtone. From theſe and the like Conſiderations, this Piece was at firſt conceiv'd, and is now produc'd for your Service, and for ſuch of your Female Companions or Acquaintance as you ſhall think fit to communicate it to; and I hope it will give Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>Be pleas'd therefore to conſider, that 'tis the duty of every Chriſtian to read and be acquainted with the Holy Scriptures. And though the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> denied the reading of them to the Laity, pretending that the Vulgation of them was the cauſe of ſo many Hereſies abroad in the World; yet, by the leave of the Fathers aſſembled in that Particular General Council, we cann't conceive how a Country Plough-Jobber, ſhould, by read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, be the Author of an Opinion, either
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56476:12"/> Orthodox or Erroneous: But, as might eaſily be prov'd if it were to the preſent purpoſe, the Original of all Sects were Men, who to ſhew their Parts and Learning, took upon them to ſcrutiniſe and enquire into the Senſe of Holy Writ, and ſo ſpread the prime Infection. I will trouble you with but an Inſtance or two to this purpoſe, and ſo proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arius,</hi> that known Heretick, as well for his Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as the many Proſelites he gain'd to his Party, meeting with that Text, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 3. <hi>This is life eternal, to know thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent;</hi> thought of a trick, by miſplacing a Point, to ſeclude Chriſt from being True God. In the Original 'tis, <hi>This is life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>To know thee only to be true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</hi> But he puts the Comma after the Particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (<hi>only</hi>), and ſo corrupts the Senſe by miſplacing the Point; a trick which certainly none but a Scholar could have thought on. Thus we find <hi>Gregory the Great</hi> openly aſſerting, That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhould call himſelf Univerſal Biſhop, was Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; but the ſucceeding Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> diſputed the contrary, and arrogated to themſelves the Title.</p>
            <p>I might likewiſe urge the Feuds of the <hi>Franciſcans</hi> and <hi>Dominicans,</hi> and other Orders of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to prove that all Quarrellings and jangling Diſputes about Matters of Religion, have in all Ages been broach'd by Men of Learning. But to come nearer home; would it not be very abſurd, to imagin that ſuch a ſilly fancy as <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> could ever have been heard of, or ſo long upheld among us, if ſome ſuch Man as <hi>Penn,</hi> who is thought no great ſtranger in a College of Fame, had not at firſt inſinuated it into ſome poor ignorant People, who were not able to reſiſt his Logick, or it may be, were more taken up in their worldly Employments, than the Study of Holy Scriptures? And indeed it is not probable,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56476:12"/> that one who is better skill'd in the management of a Plough, than a Logical Argument, ſhould be able to define in Matters of Faith and Doctrin. It may be ſooner prov'd that the principal Authors and Abetters of moſt of our Diviſions, came from <hi>Rome,</hi> than that they ſprung from ignorant People reading the Scriptures. And if you pleaſe to peruſe theſe Papers, you'll find, that the Chuch of <hi>Rome</hi> in that Council, had other Ends in denying the Scriptures to the Common People, than the Suppreſſing of Sectaries, as they pretended. I come therefore to the buſineſs.</p>
            <p>I propos'd to your Conſideration, the Duty incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on every Chriſtian to read and underſtand the Holy Scriptures. This I preſent to your Meditation in the firſt place, as Preparatory to that which is to follow: It being my intent, in this Undertaking, to have to do with nothing but Scripture Quotations. And ſo I begin.</p>
            <p>Deut. 6. 6.—<hi>And theſe words which I command thee this day, ſhall be in thine heart. And thou ſhalt teach them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently unto thy children, and ſhalt talk of them when thou ſitteſt in thine houſe, and when thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou lyeſt down, and when thou riſeſt up. And thou ſhalt bind them for a ſign upon thine hand, and they ſhall be as frontlets between thine eyes. And thou ſhalt write them upon the door poſts of thy houſe, and on thy gates.</hi>—The words were ſpoken to the whole Congregation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and need not be explain'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 18.—<hi>And it ſhall be when the king of Iſrael ſitteth upon the throne of his kingdom, that he ſhall write him a copy of this Law in a book, out of that which is before the Prieſts the Levites; and it ſhall be with him, and he ſhall read therein all the days of his life,</hi> &amp;c.—Where give me leave to take Notice, That it being impoſſible to keep the Scriptures from the Eye of the more Ingenious Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56476:13"/> they have been furniſhed with a Vulgar Latin Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the Bible, which they call (though falſly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) St. <hi>Jerome</hi>'s; and leſt the Corruptions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they had (prudently) loaded it, ſhould be diſcovered, Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the V. in the Year 1578, publiſhed a <hi>Greek</hi> Copy, purpoſely forg'd by Cardinal <hi>Carapha,</hi> to make Men believe, That the <hi>Latin</hi> was agreeable to the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1. 8.—<hi>This Book of the law ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, but thou ſhalt meditate therein day and night, that thou mayeſt obſerve to do all that is written therein</hi>—This is the Pſalmiſt's Character of a Good Man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>His delight is in the law of the Lord, and in his law doth he meditate day and night.</hi> This was the Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of <hi>Apollos, Acts</hi> 18. 24. <hi>That he was not only an eloquent Man, but mighty in the Scriptures:</hi> And this was the Confidence of the Apoſtle concerning the <hi>Romans, Rom.</hi> 15. After he had told them, verſe 4. That <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever things were written aforetime, were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures might have hope;</hi> At the 14. Verſe he concludes, <hi>And I my ſelf alſo am perſwaded of you, my brethren, that ye alſo are full of goodneſs, filled with all knowledge, and able to admoniſh one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16.—<hi>Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you richly in all wiſdom, teaching and admoniſhing one another in pſalms and hymns and ſpiritual ſongs,</hi> &amp;c.—And Ch. 4. 16. <hi>When this epiſtle is read amongſt you, cauſe that it be read alſo in the church of the Laodiceans, and that ye likewiſe read the Epiſtle from Laodicea.</hi> Parallel to which is his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1 Epiſt. 5. 27. <hi>I charge you by the Lord, that this epiſtle be read to all the holy brethren.</hi>—And indeed it would be ſome Comfort, if they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> could but have the Goſpel read in the Congregation, purely and without Adulteration, in a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56476:13"/> Tongue underſtood by the Common People. This would be much more to Edification than a few Stories out of the Golden Legend, or the Hiſtory of S. <hi>George</hi>'s killing the Dragon; which I aſſure you, Madam, is a part of the Service of his Day, and in their Prayer to him they ſolemnly commemorate this Act of his, as if it were as True as the Goſpel. But,</p>
            <p>Laſtly, S. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſpeaking of the Voice from Heaven, <hi>This is my beloved ſon, in whom I am well pleaſed;</hi> ſays, <hi>We have alſo a more ſure word of prophecy, whereunto ye do well that ye take heed, as unto a Light that ſhineth in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day-ſtar ariſe in your hearts: knowing this firſt, That no prophecy of the ſcripture is of any private interpretation,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 19, 20. I give you both Verſes, becauſe I know ſome Men would be apt to object the laſt to the firſt: But we may obſerve, That if S. <hi>Peter</hi> does condemn the Private Interpretation of Scriptures, he does not condemn the Private Reading of them, but ſays, That <hi>all men will do well, if they take good heed to them, as to a more ſure word than a voice from heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, Madam, I think it ſufficiently appears, That it is the neceſſary Duty of every Chriſtian to Read, and be well acquainted with the Scriptures, they being the <hi>pillar and ground of truth, and the power of God unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, if after all, it is objected, as I ſuppoſe it will, That the Scriptures are dark, and hard to be underſtood; be pleaſed to conſider with me theſe few Texts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deut</hi> 30. 11.—<hi>This commandment which I command thee this day, is not hidden from thee, neither is it far off; it is not in heaven, that thou ſhouldeſt ſay, Who ſhall go up for us to heaven, and bring it unto us that we may hear it and do it? neither is it beyond the ſea, that thou ſhouldeſt ſay, Who ſhall go over the ſea for us, and bring it unto us, that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56476:14"/> we may hear it and do it? But the word is very nigh unto thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou mayest do it</hi>—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119. 130.—<hi>The entrance of thy words giveth light: It giveth underſtanding to the ſimple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 6.—<hi>A ſcorner ſeeketh wiſdom, and findeth it not; but knowledge is eaſie to him that underſtandeth.</hi>—I take theſe to be ſufficient indications of the Plainneſs and Intelligibleneſs of the Law. But we have God's own Word, if he may be believed, That the Goſpel ſhould be much more eaſie to be underſtood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 33.—<hi>But this ſhall be the covenant that I will make with the houſe of Iſrael, after thoſe days, ſaith the Lord, I will put my law into their inward parts, and write it in their hearts; and they ſhall teach no more every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, ſaying, Know the Lord; for they ſhall all know me, from the leaſt unto the greateſt of them, ſaith the Lord.</hi>—And that the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Scriptures is not reſerved for the more Learned of Mankind only, is plain from our Saviours own Words, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 25. <hi>I thank thee, O father, Lord, of heaven and earth, becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them unto Babes: Even ſo, Father, for ſo it ſeemed good in thy ſight.</hi> And when his Diſciples asked him, <hi>Why he ſpake to the Jews in parables,</hi> he anſwered and ſaid unto them, <hi>Becauſe it is given unto you to know the myſteries of the kingdom of heaven, but to them it is not given,</hi> Matth. 13. 11. And we know that his Diſciples were, for the moſt part Poor, Ignorant, Unlearned; and among the Jews came very often the Scribes, Phariſees and great Doctors. All that I ſhall add, at preſent, to compleat this Subject, is, That Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in the Scriptures is very Dangerous.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is generally the Cauſe of Mens commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all maner of ſins.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:56476:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1. 3.—<hi>The ox knoweth his owner, and the Aſs his maſters crib; but Iſrael doth not know, my people doth not conſider.</hi>—God Almighty had been ſo Gracious to them, as to give them his law firſt, for them to read, and the Prophets afterwards to explain it, that they might know and underſtand his Will therein; but they would neither read the one, nor give ear to the other. And this, without doubt, was the cauſe of God's cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, <hi>How long ſhall I ſee the ſtandard, and hear the ſound of the trumpet? for my people is fooliſh, they have not known me, they are ſottiſh children, and they have no underſtanding; they are wiſe to do evil, but to do good they have no knowledge,</hi> Jer. 4. 21. and Chap. 5. 21. <hi>Hear now this, O fooliſh peopole, and without <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, which have eyes and ſee not, ears and hear not.</hi> Becauſe they would neither read the Law, nor give Ear to the Prophets, therefore they were juſtly called <hi>Sottiſh Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, a fooliſh people, and without underſtanding;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were <hi>wiſe to do evil, but not to do good.</hi> For it is moſt certain, The Devil will be ſure to make his beſt of Ignorance, and uſe his utmoſt endeavour to keep Men in it; becauſe the more Light Men have, the more Work they can do, and the better they are informed, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they will act here, and ſo he will be like to loſe their Company hereafter. I think, then, that S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s <hi>tolle, lege,</hi> will be good Advice to all that are willing to live Virtuous Lives; and as <hi>Luther</hi>'s advice to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, was to read the Books of the Kings, for their Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation how to Rule well; ſo, that all Men would read the Holy Scriptures in general, would be good Counſel, becauſe they afford the beſt Inſtructions for living well.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ignorance in the Scriptures is dangerous, becauſe it is the greateſt Reaſon of Mens running into all ſorts of Errors.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:56476:15"/>
            <p>When the Sadducees propoſed to our Saviour the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of the Woman that had had ſeven Husbands, ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, <hi>whoſe wife ſhe ſhould be at the reſurrection?</hi> falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſing, If there ever would be a Reſurrection, there would alſo be Marrying and giving in Marriage at the Reſurrection; Jeſus anſwered and ſaid unto them, <hi>Ye do err, not knowing the Scriptures.</hi> And here, Madam, I might take notice of the Subtlety of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in denying the Scriptures to the Laity, becauſe maintaining ſo many Errors ſo directly contrary to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, that any diſcerning Eye muſt needs diſcover them: Such are Purgatory, Pope's Pardons, Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Images, praying to Saints and Angels, and the like. But our Lord ſaid of the Phariſees, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. 14. <hi>Let them alone; they are blind leaders of the blind: And if the blind lead the blind both ſhall fall into the ditch.</hi> I ſhall ſay nothing therefore to theſe, at preſent, but proceed,</p>
            <p n="3">3. To ſhew, That Ignorance in the Scriptures is very Dangerous, becauſe as it is the cauſe of Sin and Error, ſo by Sin and Error, it muſt conſequently be the cauſe of Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſay</hi> 5. 13.—<hi>Therefore my people are gone into captivity, becauſe they have no knowledge; and their honourable Men are famiſhed, and their multitude dryed up with thirſt. Therefore hell hath enlarged her ſelf, and opened her mouth without meaſure; and their glory, and their multitude, and their pomp, and he that rejoyceth ſhall deſcend into it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſalm</hi> 95. 10.—<hi>Forty years long was I grieved with this generation, and ſaid, It is a people that do err in their hearts, and they have not known my ways: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto whom, therefore, I ſware in my wrath, that they ſhould not enter into my reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 24.—<hi>Becauſe I have called, and ye refuſed, I have ſtretched out my hand and no man regarded; but ye
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56476:15"/> have ſet at nought all my counſel, and would none of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof; I alſo will laugh at your calamity, I will mock when your fear cometh; when your fear cometh as deſolation, and your deſtruction cometh as a whirl-wind, when diſtreſs and anguiſh come upon you: Then ſhall ye call upon me, but I will not anſwer, ye ſhall ſeek me, but ye ſhall not find me; for that ye hated knowledge, and did not chuſe the fear of the Lord.</hi>—But to come a little nearer home; Chriſt Jeſus has brought Life and Immortality to Light by the Goſpel. But this, ſays he, <hi>is the condemnation,</hi> by way of Eminence, <hi>That light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather than light, becauſe their deeds are evil: For every one that doth evil hateth the light, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cometh he to the light, leſt his deeds ſhould be reproved; but he that does truth, cometh to the light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt, that they are wrought in God,</hi> Joh. 3. 19. And ſurely, Madam, If they that deny us the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, had not ſomething to be aſhamed of, they would not ſhew themſelves ſo much concerned to keep People in Darkneſs. It muſt needs be a Device of the Devil, to keep Men in Ignorance, that they might be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; according to the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3. <hi>If our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt; In whom the God of this world has blinded the minds of them which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not, leſt the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the image of God, ſhould ſhine upon them. But we know that Chriſt will one day be revealed in flaming fire, to take vengeance on them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 Theſſal. 1. 8. If it is objected, That this Text ſpeaks of Heathen Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors; we may anſwer, That thoſe Chriſtians, who are not acquainted with, and conſequently, not obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the Goſpel of Chriſt, are worſe than Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. I beſeech you, Madam, to conſider, If it was through Ignorance of the Scriptures, the Jews cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56476:16"/> the Lord of Glory, as the Apoſtle ſays it was, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 8. We that are Chriſtians, had beſt take heed, That we do not through Ignorance crucifie him again. And if it was a Shame for the <hi>Corinthians</hi> not to know the Scriptures, in the very dawning and twilight of Chriſtianity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 34, what an abominable ſhame muſt it needs be, for us, after almoſt ſeventeen hundred Years, to know no more, or it may be, not ſo much?</p>
            <p>To conclude this Point: The Apoſtle dedicates his Firſt <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians, To All that in Every place call on the name of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> And what he ſhould do ſo for, unleſs he intended it ſhould be read by All, I can't imagin. If he intended it only for the Fathers of that Church, he might in fewer words, and conſequently with leſs trouble, have ſaid, To the Elders of the Church at <hi>Corinth;</hi> or elſe directed it to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of that Church only. But he knew the Scriptures were able to make Men <hi>wiſe unto ſalvation,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would have all Men read them. And our bleſſed Saviour knew that the Jews thought they had Eternal Life in the Scriptures, therefore he bids 'em <hi>Search</hi> them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 39. The Injunction is the ſame upon Chriſtians alſo. And then certainly, if the Captain and Author of our Salvation bids us <hi>Search,</hi> we may, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Inſinuations of ſome bold Men to the contrary. By what Rule elſe ſhould we try the Spirits, whether they be of God, as St. <hi>John</hi> adviſeth us, 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 4. 1. if not by the Rule of God's Word? Upon this account there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, among others, we are bound to read, ſearch, and be well acquainted with the Scriptures. I preſume then, after all that has been produc'd to prove this firſt Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, what the Evangeliſt ſays of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> Chap. 1. 3. may on good grounds be attributed to the reſt of the Sacred Writings; <hi>Bleſſed is he that readeth, and they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56476:16"/> that hear the words of this prophecy, and keep thoſe things that are written therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, Madam, having made good from Scripture Teſtimonies, the Neceſſity of being acquainted with the Scriptures; though I have already gone beyond the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary bounds of an Epiſtle, yet I crave leave to treſpaſs a little farther on your Patience, in giving you a curſory view of ſome of the Principal Doctrins of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and demonſtrating how contrary they are to the Word of Truth. In order to which, I ſhall with all poſſible brevity enquire,</p>
            <p n="1">I. Whether any Man can do more than he ought to do?</p>
            <p n="2">II. Whether any Man by his own Works can merit Heaven?</p>
            <p n="3">III. To whom it belongeth to Forgive Sins?</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Whether the Scriptures warrant Worſhiping of Images, or Praying to Saints and Angels?</p>
            <p n="5">V. Whether there is any ſuch Place as Purgatory?</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Whether the Maſs is a Sacrifice for Quick and Dead?</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Whether the Doctrin of Tranſubſtantiation can be maintain'd by Scripture?</p>
            <p>The firſt Enquiry muſt be, whether any Man can do more than he ought to do? Where we are to conſider, That though a Man, as a Chriſtian, is in the ſtate of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56476:17"/> Grace, yet he is not in the ſtate of Innocence, nor can be, till he arrives at the ſtate of Glory, where all Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities will be done away. For as he is Fleſh and Blood, liable to be tempted to evil, and apt to commit it, he muſt expect to meet with Afflictions and Croſſes from the World without, and the Suggeſtions and Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Devil from within: And being naturally more prone to Evil than Good, I think it a hard thing to ſay, That 'tis in his power to do more Good than is requir'd he ſhould do, and a harder to prove it.</p>
            <p>Under the Law, Men were not able to keep the Law perfectly, nor to walk in the Commandments of God as they ought. For <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, who took them from God's mouth, and gave them to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> err'd in ſo much, that he muſt not enter the <hi>promiſed Land.</hi> That Text, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 11. 15. has been objected by ſome Gentlemen of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but plainly to no purpoſe. For any one may ſee, that <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s keeping the Commandments, was only his doing thoſe things he was commanded to do, in order to eſtabliſh the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Inheritance of the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> And we find the ſame <hi>Joſhua</hi> in another place aſſerting the impoſſibility of ſerving God, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24. 19. at leaſt he did not believe Men could do more.</p>
            <p>It may be objected, That the light of the Goſpel is much clearer than that of the Law, and the burthen ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to be born, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But for all that, 'tis certain the Goſpel requires as full and perfect Obedience as ever the Law did. Nay, it proceeds farther; for under the Law Men thought it no great Crime to murther their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in his good Name, ſo they let his Body alone: They alſo thought it no Sin to Luſt after a Woman, provided they did not come to Action. But under the Goſpel our Saviour tells us the contrary <hi>Ye have heard, that it was ſaid by them of old time, Thou ſhalt not kill; and whoſoever
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56476:17"/> ſhall kill, ſhall be in danger of the Judgment. But I ſay unto you, That whoſoever is angry with his Brother without a cauſe, ſhall be in danger of the Judgment; and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall ſay unto his Brother, Racha, ſhall be in danger of the Council: but whoſoever ſhall ſay, Thou Fool, ſhall be in danger of Hell Fire.</hi> Again, <hi>Ye have heard that it was ſaid by them of old time, Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery. But I ſay unto you, That whoſoever looketh on a Woman, to lust after her, hath committed Adultery with her already in his heart,</hi> Matth. 5. 21, 22, 27, 28. So that we may ſee, though the Law was ſuch a <hi>yoke as neither we nor our Fore-fathers were able to bear,</hi> Act. 15. 10. yet the Yoke of the Goſpel is not ſo light as to be run away with. As eaſie as it is, 'tis very irkſom to Fleſh and Blood; yet 'tis what we muſt bear ſo long as we live, and then it is God's mere Mercy, if the heavier yoke of Everlaſting Miſery is not laid on us inſtead of it.</p>
            <p>If Man has Free-will to do good as well as evil, yet, <hi>I know that in me (that is, in my fleſh) dwelleth no good thing: for to will is preſent with me, but how to perform that which is good, I find not. For the good that I would, I do not; but the evil which I would not, that I do. Now if I do that I would not, it is no more I that do it, but ſin that dwelleth in me.</hi> (And on the contrary, <hi>if I do that good I would, it is no more I that do it, but the grace of God that is in me,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 18.) <hi>I find then a Law, that when I would do good, evil is preſent with me. For I delight in the Law of God, after the inward man. But I ſee another law in my members, warring againſt the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity to the law of ſin, which is in my members,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 18. And he at laſt concludes, <hi>So then with the mind I my ſelf ſerve the Law of God; but with the fleſh the law of ſin.</hi> To which we may add
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56476:18"/> what the ſame Apoſtle ſays, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. <hi>But the natural man</hi> (that is, fleſh and blood) <hi>receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſs unto him; neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi> And then certainly our Free-will can do us little good, towards making us do more than we ſhould, when by reaſon of the ſtubborneſs of our Fleſh, we can't do what we would. But the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>That we are not able to do any thing of our ſelves, but 'tis God that worketh in us both to will and do after his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> Phil. 2. 13. And our Saviour himſelf ſays, <hi>That no man can come unto him, unleſs the Father draw him,</hi> Joh. 6. 44. Therefore I think it ſtrange that a Man ſhould be able to do more than he can: 'Tis a Contradiction. Certainly he that made us, can tell beſt what we can do: And he ſays, <hi>That the heart of man is only evil continually,</hi> Gen. 6. 5. &amp; 8. 21. If then we are naturally more prone to do evil than good, how is it poſſible for us to be better than we ſhould be? And if under the Goſpel we muſt obſerve every Punctilio ſo ſtrictly, as not to be angry with our Neighbour, not to look on a Woman to luſt after her, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how are we able to do all that's required of us? The Apoſtle St. <hi>James</hi> goes a ſtep farther; <hi>If ye fulfil the Royal Law, according to the Scripture, Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf, ye do well: But if ye have reſpect to perſons, ye commit ſin, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the Law as Tranſgreſſors,</hi> Jam. 2. 9. To have reſpect to Perſons in civil Converſation, one would think a ſmall matter, to make one guilty of the breach of the Law; but ſo it is. And our Saviour goes farther yet, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 43. <hi>Ye have heard that it hath been ſaid, Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour, and hate thine Enemy: But I ſay unto you, Love your Enemies, bleſs them that curſe you, do good to them that hate you,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56476:18"/> and pray for them which deſpightfully uſe you and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute you.</hi> This is a hard leſſon, and not agreeable to Fleſh and Blood; yet 'tis made the condition of becoming the Children of our Father which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>From what has been ſaid, we may gather, That if any Man can do what he is required to do, he cannot do more. And if, as we are told, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi> And if a <hi>juſt man falleth ſeven times a day,</hi> Prov. 24. 16. Who can boaſt of being righteous over much? Nay, where is there a Man ſo good, as that he may <hi>number his offences?</hi> Holy <hi>David</hi> could not, though <hi>a man after God's own heart.</hi> We read of but one man, throughout the whole Book of God, who was <hi>without ſin,</hi> and that was the man <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> yet it was never ſaid of him, that he did more than fulfil the Will of his Father. And for us, born in ſin, and conceived in corruption, to ſay we can do more!—I cannot expreſs the Folly and Nonſenſe of it. By ſo doing, we ſhould make God our Debtor, who is Debtor to no Man. If they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can brag of any works of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erogation, they are ſuch as theſe; The hallowing Daggers for the cutting off Princes that are not for their turn: The ſacrificing all they pleaſe to call Hereticks: The denying the Scriptures in a tongue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by the Vulgar: And ſeveral others which might be named, concerning which they may indeed be ask'd, Who hath required theſe things at your hands? But we of the Church of <hi>England</hi> know of nothing to be done, more than what is our duty to do. We know the Preachers Doctrin was, <hi>Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thy hand findeth for thee to do, do it with thy might,</hi> Eccl. 9. 10. And our Lord and Maſter's Advice is, <hi>when we have done all we can,</hi> to acknowledge our ſelves
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56476:19"/> 
               <hi>but unprofitable Servants;</hi> having done only what <hi>was our duty to do,</hi> Luk. 17. 10. For no Man lives and ſins not. <hi>If therefore we ſay that we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us,</hi> 1 Joh. 1. 8. Nay, we make God a Liar, who hath ſaid, <hi>there is not one that doth good,</hi> Pſal 14. 1, 3. In a word, if there is a Devil to tempt, we are ſtill in danger of ſinning. And if every thought will be brought in to Judgment, who can call himſelf Inncent? 'Tis my opinion, that inſtead of thinking we can do more than our Duty; Every Man ſhould rather repent of the ſins, as well of Omiſſion, as Commiſſion he is daily guilty of; and with the Pſalmiſt cry out, <hi>Who can underſtand his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors? cleanſe thou me from ſecret faults,</hi> Pſal. 19. 12. For our Saviour's cenſure on the moſt righteous, is, <hi>Except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh,</hi> Luk. 13. 3, 5. To conclude this firſt <hi>Quere;</hi> if it were poſſible for any Man to over-do his Duty, I would ask any reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Man, Whether, when he has done more than he ought to have done, he would not commit a great ſin in thinking ſo, and a greater in ſaying ſo? If the Affirmative holds good, then the poor Man has ſtill ſome part of his Duty to perform, <hi>viz.</hi> to repent of that ſin; and ſo <hi>in infinitum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>II. The ſecond Enquiry propoſed, was, Whether a Man by his own Works can merit Heaven?</p>
            <p>Here, Madam, be pleaſed to conſider with me theſe few following Texts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 9. 4.—<hi>Speak not thou in thine heart, after that the Lord thy God hath caſt them out from before thee, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, For my righteouſneſs the Lord hath brought me in to poſſeſs this Land; but for the wickedneſs of theſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:56476:19"/> &amp;c.—The Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> of which this Text ſpeaks, is generally looked on as a Type of Heaven: And then this is plain enough.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> 9. 30.—<hi>If I waſh my ſelf with ſnow-water, and make my hands never ſo clean; yet thou ſhalt plunge me in the ditch, and my own cloaths ſhall abhor me,</hi> &amp;c. And Chap. 15. 14.—<hi>What is man, that he ſhould be clean? and he which is born of a woman, that he ſhould be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous?</hi> Verſe 16. <hi>How much more abominable and filthy is man, which drinketh iniquity like water?</hi>—All ſpoken by one, whoſe Fellow was not to be found upon the Face of the Earth for Vertue; and therefore if any could boaſt, he might.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. 3.—<hi>If thou, Lord, ſhouldſt mark iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, O Lord, who ſhould ſtand? But there is forgiveneſs with thee, that thou mayeſt be feared.</hi>—And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143. 2.—<hi>Enter not into judgment with thy ſervant, for in thy ſight ſhall no man living be juſtified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53. 6.—<hi>All we like ſheep have gone aſtray; we have turned every one to his own way, and the Lord hath laid on him the iniquities of us all.</hi>—And Chap. 64. 6.—<hi>But we are all as unclean things; and all our righteouſneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are as filthy rags, and we do all fade as a leaf, and our iniquity like the wind hath taken us away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 10.—<hi>As it is written, There is none righteous, no not one; there is none that underſtandeth, there is none that ſeeketh after God; they are all gone out of the way, they are altogether become unprofitable, there is none that doth good, no not one. Their throat is an open ſepulchre, with their tongues they have uſed deceit, the poiſon of aſps is under their lips, whoſe mouth is full of curſing and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, their feet are ſwift to ſhed blood, deſtruction and miſery are in their ways, and the way of peace have they not known; there is no fear of God before their eyes.</hi>—All this is ſpoken of all Mankind in general, both Jews and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56476:20"/> Gentiles; and if it be true, what can any Man find in himſelf to challenge Heaven as his due?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 23.—Eternal Life is called, <hi>The gift of God, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>—Now if Eternal Life be a Gift, I would fain know how a Gift can be Merited? And if it be for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, I would know whether the ſame Gift can be ſaid to be Merited by him for us, and by us for our ſelves too? if this is affirmed, then ſomething to this purpoſe muſt follow, That the Paſſion and Death of Chriſt are Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant, and partly not, becauſe a Man, as a Chriſtian at leaſt, may Merit, and conſequently enjoy Heaven, by his own Works, without the Application of Chriſts Merits; which would be very Abſurd, to ſay no worſe of it: But if it be denyed, then the Conſequence will be this, That let a Man merit what he will, he muſt be beholding to the Merits of Chriſt for his Admiſſion into Heaven, at laſt.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 4.—<hi>For I know nothing by my ſelf, yet am I not hereby juſtified; but he that judgeth me is the Lord.</hi>—Let us then ſuppoſe a Man to be in the Apoſtles Caſe, in my Opinion ſuch a Man could have but little Comfort from his own Merits, if he being ſo perfect as not to know any evil by himſelf, ſhould not for all that be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of his Juſtification. I would ask one of theſe Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Gentlemen, in the Words of the Apoſtle, at the ſeventh Verſe of the ſame Chapter; <hi>Who maketh thee to differ from another? and what haſt thou that thou didst not receive? now if thou didſt receive it, why doſt thou glory as if thou hadſt not received it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 8.—<hi>For by grace ye are ſaved, through Faith; and that not of your ſelves, it is the gift of God; not of works, leſt any man ſhould boaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:56476:20"/>
            <p>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 9.—<hi>Who hath ſaved us, and called us with a holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpoſe and grace; which was given us in Chriſt Jeſus before the world began.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 5.—<hi>Not by works of righteouſneſs, which we have done, but according to his mercy he ſaved us,</hi> &amp;c. And many more you will meet with in reading; but by theſe few you may judge how available our works, even the very beſt we can do, are to ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Before I leave this Point, I preſume it will not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, if I add ſomething, in this Place, touching Juſtification by Faith: In which, for brevity ſake, I ſhall do little more than ſet down the moſt pertinent Texts of Scripture, and leave the reſt to your Ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And in the firſt place,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 6.—<hi>Abraham believed in the Lord, and he counted it to him for righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Habak.</hi> 2. 4.—<hi>Behold, his ſoul which is lifted up, is not upright in him; but the juſt ſhall live by his Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 12.—<hi>But as many as received him, to them gave he power to become the ſons of God, even to them that believe on his name.</hi> And Chap. 3. 16. <hi>For God ſo lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the world, that he gave his only begotten ſon, that whoſoever believeth on him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi>—</p>
            <p>When our Saviour went to raiſe the Ruler of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue's Daughter, he bid him, <hi>only believe,</hi> Mark, 5. 36.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 23.—<hi>To him give all the Prophets witneſs. That through his name, whoſoever believeth in him, ſhall receive remiſſion of ſins.</hi> And Chap. 16. 31. When the Keeper of the Priſon, wherein <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> were, asked them, <hi>What he ſhould do to be ſaved,</hi> their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was, <hi>Believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved, and thy houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:56476:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 23.—<hi>For we have all ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God, being juſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Jeſus Chriſt; whom God hath ſet forth to be a propitiation, through faith in his blood, to declare his righteouſneſs for the remiſſion of ſins that are paſt, through the forbearance of God: To declare, I ſay, at this time his righteouſneſs, that he might be juſt, and the juſtifier of him which believeth in Jeſus. Where is boaſting then? it is excluded. By what law? of works? Nay, but by the law of Faith; therefore we conclude, that a man is juſtified by faith, without the deeds of the law.</hi>—If you conſider this Quotation throughly, you will find it as compleat to the purpoſe, as can be deſired. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, I'll preſent you with a few more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 1.—<hi>What ſhall we ſay then, that Abraham our father, as pertaining to the fleſh, hath found? no, for if Abraham were juſtified by works, he hath whereof to glory, but not before God; for what ſay the Scriptures? Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham believed God, and it was counted to him for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: And to him that worketh not, but believeth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi>—Where, by the way, the Word (<hi>ungodly</hi>) in this Text, muſt not be taken to mean Impenitent Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for they, as ſuch, can have no Right to Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; but as no man is Upright in the Sight of God, he is ſaid, in the Beſt of Men, <hi>to juſtifie ungodly, freely by his grace,</hi> in the foregoing Chapter, Verſe 23, 24. So that this makes doubly for my Purpoſe, ſhewing, firſt, That Juſtification comes by Faith; and alſo, That thoſe that are Juſtified, being Sinners before God, cannot with Reaſon boaſt of the Merit of Works.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1.—<hi>Therefore being juſtified by faith, we have peace with God, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> And Chap. 10. 8. <hi>The word is nigh thee, in thy mouth and in thy
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56476:21"/> heart; that is the word of faith which we preach, That if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt believe in thy heart, that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 16. 21.—<hi>Knowing that a man is not juſtified by the works of the law, but by the faith of Jeſus Chriſt, even we have believed in Jeſus Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by the faith of Chriſt, and not by the works of the law, for by the works of the law ſhall no fleſh be juſtified. I do not fruſtrate the grace of God; for if righteouſneſs come by the law, then Chriſt is dead in vain.</hi> And Chap. 3. 11.—And the Scripture foreſeeing that God would Juſtifie the Heathen through Faith, preached before the Goſpel unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>In thee ſhall all nations be bleſſed. But that no man is juſtified by the law in the ſight of God, it is evident, for the juſt ſhall live by faith: For in Jeſus Chriſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumciſion nor uncircumciſion availeth any thing, but faith which worketh by love.</hi>—Let that Text. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 8. above cited, ſumm up all; <hi>For by grace ye are ſaved, through faith; and that not of your ſelves, it is the gift of God, not of works leſt any man ſhould boaſt.</hi> Neither have I been at all this Pains, from a ſolifidian Principle, to endeavour to ſeclude Good Works from being the Fruits of a lively Faith: For ſo I ſhould fruſtrate the Grace of God. And I preſume, Madam, you know my Opinion better than to think ſo; my Intent was only to ſhew, How Erronious it is to ſuppoſe Merit from Works, eſpecially according to the Doctrin of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> That Men may Merit for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others. To conclude this Point, give me leave to preſent to your Meditation the Heinouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Original Sin only, and then I'll leave you to Judge, if, for all that, and the many Actual Sins we daily commit, God will be gracious to us, and receive us unto his Glory, how little Reaſon we
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:56476:22"/> have to boaſt of that <hi>Nothing</hi> we have done to Merit his Favour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 5.—<hi>And God ſaw that the wickedneſs of man was great in the earth, and that every imagination of the thoughts of his heart was only evil continually; and it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented the Lord that he had made man on the earth, and it grieved him at his heart: And the Lord ſaid, I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy man, whom I have created, from the face of the earth, both man and beaſt, and the creeping thing, and the fowls of the air; for it repenteth me that I have made them.</hi>—I think no man can deny Original Sin to be the Cauſe of all this; and then, how Heinous a thing that is, which is the Cauſe of ſo much Diſpleaſure in God, I ſubmit to any perſon to Judge. You will read to the ſame Purpoſe, Verſe 11, 12, 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> 14. 4.—<hi>Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean? not one.</hi> For, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 5. <hi>Behold I was ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in iniquity, and in ſin did my mother conceive me. Prov.</hi> 20. 9. <hi>Who then can ſay, I have made my heart clean, I am pure from my ſin? Eccl.</hi> 7. 29. <hi>For lo, this only have I found, That God made man upright</hi> at firſt, but ſince they have fallen away from that Upright State, they <hi>have ſought out many Inventions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 9.—<hi>The heart is deceitful above all things, and deſperately wicked, who can know it?</hi> For, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. 19. <hi>Out of the heart proceed evil thoughts, murthers, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, fornications, thefts, falſe-witneſs, blaſphemies, and all things that defile a man.</hi> And the Reaſon of all this is, Becauſe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 6. <hi>That which is born of the fleſh, is fleſh.</hi> Man, as he is Fleſh and Blood, is naturally fleſhly minded. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 14. <hi>For we know that the law is ſpiritual, but I am carnal, ſold under ſin; for that which I do, I allow not, for what I would, that do I not, but what I hate, that I do.</hi> And ſo, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>All are by nature the children of wrath.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:56476:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 15.—<hi>Then when luſt hath conceived, it bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth ſin; and when 'tis finiſhed, bringeth forth death.</hi>—Our firſt Parents luſted after the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fruit, and that brought forth the ſin of breaking the Commandment; and that ſin brought forth Death. And <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12. <hi>As by one man ſin entred into the world, and death by ſin; ſo death paſſed upon all men, for that all, in him, have ſinned.</hi>—Wherefore if all are guilty of Original Sin, and that guilt makes us Children of Wrath, and conſequently Heirs of Damnation, I don't ſee any reaſon we have to boaſt of our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but rather we have too much cauſe to bewail our wretchedneſs, and to pray continually againſt the inevitable miſery we are liable to undergo, for all the good works we have done, or can do, unleſs God be more merciful to the beſt of us, than we deſerve.</p>
            <p>And though by Baptiſm the guilt of Original Sin is waſhed away; yet 'tis more than probable, that the firſt Actual Sin brings it again. For, as he that by amendment of life turns to God, his former ſins ſhall not be remembred; ſo, he that returns from the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, his righteouſneſs ſhall be blotted out and forgotten, and all his former iniquities ſhall teſtifie againſt him. To conclude; from what has been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd, this at preſent occurs to our Obſervation; That though there is no ſuch thing in truth, as a Solifidian Juſtice, but every Man that will be ſaved, muſt be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced with a Faith that works by Love; yet after all we can do, we muſt expect Salvation by Faith in Chriſt's Blood, and not from our own worthineſs.</p>
            <p>III. The Third Enquiry propos'd, was, To whom it belongs to Forgive Sins?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3. 8.—<hi>Salvation belongeth to the Lord.</hi>—49. 7.—<hi>None of them can by any means redeem his brother,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:56476:23"/> nor give to God a ranſom for him. For the redemption of their ſoul is precious.</hi>—And 37. 39. <hi>The ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the righteous is of the Lord.</hi> Therefore, 130. 7. <hi>Let Iſrael hope in the Lord.</hi>—It was the Pſalmiſts opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, That it belonged to God to Forgive Sins, and therefore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 14. he thus addreſſes himſelf to him; <hi>Deliver me from blood-guiltineſs, O God, thou God of my ſalvation.</hi> And thus God affirms of Himſelf, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43. 11. <hi>I, even I am the Lord; and beſide me there is no Saviour. I, even I am he that blotteth out thy tranſgreſſions for my own ſake, and will not remember thy ſins.</hi> where we may take notice, That it belongs to God to Forgive Sins; and alſo, That he Forgives them for his own ſake, which takes off all Merit by Works.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 9.—<hi>To the Lord our God belong mercies and forgiveneſſes.</hi>—It was the conſtant Opinion of the Jews: For when our Saviour ſaid to the Sick of the Palſie, <hi>Man, thy ſins are forgiven thee;</hi> the Jews, not believing him to be God as well as Man, accus'd him of Blaſphemy, ſaying, <hi>Who can forgive ſins but God only?</hi> Luk. 5. 21. So our Lord himſelf, though <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> call'd him <hi>the Lamb of God which takes away the ſins of the world,</hi> Joh. 1. 29. directs us to ask God to <hi>forgive our ſins,</hi> Mat. 6. 12. For at <hi>Verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>'Tis our heavenly Father that muſt forgive us.</hi> And thus the Apoſtle tells the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> That <hi>they being dead in their ſins, and the uncircumciſion of their fleſh, God had quickened them, and forgiven them all treſpaſſes,</hi> Col. 2. 13. From all which it appears plainly enough, That Forgiveneſs of Sin, belongs only to God.</p>
            <p>The conſequence of this, is, That if it belongs to God only to Forgive Sins, then Confeſſion of Sins is due to him alone.</p>
            <p>A Member of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is in danger of paſſing immediately into Hell, if he dies without having
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56476:23"/> confeſs'd his Sins to a Prieſt: So abſolutely neceſſary do they teach Auricular Confeſſion to be in order to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But, if we may examin it a little, I am apt to think, it will appear much like the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 5.—<hi>I acknowledged my ſins unto thee, and my iniquity have I not hid: I ſaid I will confeſs my tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions unto the Lord, and thou forgaveſt the iniquity of my ſin.</hi>—The Pſalmiſt was abſolv'd without Auricular Confeſſion, only by acknowledging his Sins to God.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>King.</hi> 8. 47.—<hi>Yet if they ſhall bethink themſelves in the Land whether they were carried Captives, and repent and make ſupplication to thee in the Land of them that carried them Captives, ſaying, We have ſinned, and have done per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſely, we have committed wickedneſs,</hi> &amp;c.—Here is no Confeſſion to a Prieſt mentioned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezra</hi> 9. 5.—<hi>And at the evening ſacrifice, I roſe up from my heavineſs, and having rent my garment and my mantle, I fell upon my knees, and ſpread out my hands unto the Lord my God, and ſaid, O my God, I am aſhamed, and bluſh to lift up my face to thee, my God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41. 4.—<hi>I ſaid, Lord be merciful unto me, and heal my ſoul, for I have ſinned againſt thee.</hi> Hence Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Sin is due to him againſt whom we have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And then 'tis due Relatively to our Neighbour, if we have done him any injury: But Properly to God, according to the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 4. <hi>Againſt thee only have I ſinned,</hi> &amp;c. when he had committed Adultery with <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> and cauſed her Husband to be ſlain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 15.—<hi>And now, O Lord our God, that haſt brought thy people forth out of the Land of Egypt with a mighty hand, and haſt gotten the renown, as at this day; we have ſinned, we have done wickedly.</hi> Therefore, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14. 20. <hi>We acknowledge, O Lord, our wickedneſs, and the iniquity of our Fathers; for we have ſinned againſt thee.</hi>—In a word; I ſhould never have done, if I ſhould quote
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:56476:24"/> all the Texts to prove Confeſſion of Sins only due to God. And therefore, becauſe you will meet with them in reading, I ſhall at preſent only refer you to the Sixth Chapter of St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel, to what our Saviour ſays there of Prayer and Faſting: For Repentance and Confeſſion being inherent parts of Prayer and Faſting, I think they may be included in the ſame Advice; which I need not have inſerted, by reaſon of your fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent uſing the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> in which 'tis evident.</p>
            <p>After all, there is not one Text, as I know of, that by any good Conſequence, makes Confeſſion to a Prieſt ſo abſolutely Neceſſary, as the Doctrin of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> does: If any will do it, and do it ſincerely, we do not deny it to be Good. But after 'tis done, without a Private Confeſſion to God, it muſt needs be Imperfect; for it is God that knows our Hearts better than we do our ſelves, and we are guilty of many Sins we know not of, as the Pſalmiſt profeſſes: Wherefore we ſhould cry out with him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 12. <hi>Who can un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand his errors? cleanſe thou me from ſecret faults.</hi> The conſequence of all is, That all Men ought to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs their Sins to God, againſt whom only they have ſinned, as to one that has the ſole Power to forgive them. Not that I deſire, in the leaſt, to diminiſh the Power of the Keys given to the Church; for I own, That our Bleſſed Lord gave Power and Authority to his Miniſters, to declare and pronounce to his People, being Penitent, the Abſolution and Remiſſion of their Sins, in his Name: But, to confine that Power to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> only; and to ſay, All that Die out of her Communion are certainly Damn'd for want of it, and to make the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> joynt-Competitor with Chriſt in the Buſineſs, is againſt the Grain, and will not digeſt in my Stomach, whatever it may do in other Mens.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:56476:24"/>
            <p>I ſhould waſt too much Time and Paper, If I ſhould examine the Groſs Nonſenſical Conſequences of Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> able to Forgive Sins, which have from thence been impoſed upon the greater part of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Ignorant ſort of People. That the Pope can at once Forgive a Man all the Sins he ever has committed, or ever ſhall be guilty of; that he can thruſt a Man into Heaven, for as long a Time as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, where he ſhall lie undiſcovered by the all-ſeeing Eye of God, and at the end of that Term be kicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell; that he can forgive the Sins of all that are in the Communion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, of all Chriſtians, nay, if he pleaſes, of the whole World at once. It has been acknowledged by many of their own Writers on this Subject, who have been guilty of the leaſt Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagance, That the Pope has Power, if he will, at one Maſs, to free all the Souls out of Purgatory. If this were true, King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt's Inference on the Poſition, was, with Abnegation of the Popes Charity, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of his unparallel'd Cruelty, That, being granted to have a Power ſo to do, he does not apply his Will to it. But I know, Madam, you are no Friend to ſuch Fancies; therefore I ſhall appeal no further than to your own Ingenuity, to judge from what has been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, Who has the Supreme and only Power to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give Sins, to whom Confeſſion properly is due, and in whoſe Name only Abſolution ought to be Pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. And ſo proceed.</p>
            <p>IV. The Fourth Enquiry propoſed, was, Whether the Scriptures warrant the Worſhiping of Images, or Praying to Saints and Angels?</p>
            <p>The Second Commandment is ſo much to our Purpoſe, that they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have prudently left it out of the Decalogue, and to make up the number, they
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:56476:25"/> cut the Tenth into two Parts; ſo the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Decalogue is this,</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods before me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Remember that thou keepeſt holy the Sabbath-day,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>Thou ſhalt do no Murther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">VII. <hi>Thou ſhalt not Steal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">VIII. <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe Witneſs againſt thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">IX. <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet thy Neighbours Wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">X. <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet thy Neighbours Houſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So that the generality of the People of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> know of no ſuch thing in Being, as the tedious Harangue againſt Images, by us called the Second Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment. However, there are Texts enough beſides, both in the Old and New Teſtaments, clearly againſt them; of which I will only give you a few of the chief.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judges</hi> 13. 15—<hi>And Manoah ſaid unto the Angel of the Lord, I pray thee, let us detain thee, until we ſhall have made ready a kid for thee. And the angel of the Lord ſaid unto Manoah, Though thou detain me, I will not eat of thy bread; and if thou wilt offer a Burnt-offering, thou muſt offer it unto the Lord. And Manoah ſaid unto the angel of the Lord, What is thy name, that when thy ſayings come to paſs, we may do thee honour? And the angel of the Lord ſaid unto him, Why askeſt thou after my name, ſeeing it is ſecret?</hi>—The Angel would not tell his Name, becauſe <hi>Manoah</hi> ſhould honour God only.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:56476:25"/>
            <p>Pſal. 29. 2.—<hi>Give unto the Lord the glory due unto his Name; worſhip the Lord in the beauty of holineſs.</hi> For <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42. 8, <hi>I am the Lord, that is my name, and my glory will I not give to another; neither my praiſe to graven Images.</hi>—And I am certain there is not one Text to the contrary; but many to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Acts 10. 25.—<hi>And as</hi> Peter <hi>was coming in,</hi> Cornelius <hi>met him, and fell down at his feet and worſhipped him. But</hi> Peter <hi>took him up, ſaying, Stand up, I my ſelf alſo am a man.</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11.—<hi>When the People ſaw what</hi> Paul <hi>had done, they lift up their voices, ſaying, in the ſpeech of</hi> Lycaonia, <hi>The Gods are come down to us in the likeneſs of Men. And they called</hi> Barnabas, Jupiter; <hi>and</hi> Paul, Mercurius; <hi>becauſe he was the chief Speaker. Then the Prieſt of</hi> Jupiter, <hi>which was before their City, brought Oxen and Garlands unto the Gates, and wou'd have done Sacrifice with the People. Which when the Apoſtles,</hi> Barnabas <hi>and</hi> Paul, <hi>heard of, they rent their Clothes, and ran in among the People, crying out, and ſaying, Sirs, why do ye theſe things? we alſo are men of like Paſſions with you,</hi> &amp;c.—I am apt to believe theſe things were done and ſuffer'd by the Providence of God, on purpoſe to ſhew, that as they were not to be worſhipp'd while they were on the Earth, ſo neither ſhou'd we pay Divine Honours to 'em now they are in Heaven. But the Apoſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> is very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>1 Cor. 1. 13.—<hi>Is Chriſt divided? was</hi> Paul <hi>crucified for you? or were ye baptized into the name of</hi> Paul? <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. 4.—<hi>Who then is</hi> Paul? <hi>and who is</hi> Apollos, <hi>but Miniſters by whom ye believed, even as the Lord gave to every man? I have planted,</hi> Apollos <hi>watered; but God gave the increaſe.</hi> So then, neither is he that planteth any thing, neither he that watereth; but <hi>God that giveth the increaſe.</hi>—Now Judge, Madam, what a horrid thing it muſt needs be to make Images and Pictures of the Saints whereby to Worſhip 'em, if it was ſo great a Crime to eſteem one of 'em before ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while they were on Earth. But as we are not to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56476:26"/> the Saints, ſo neither muſt we pay ſuch honour to Angels.</p>
            <p>Col. 2. 18.—<hi>Let no man beguile you of your reward, in a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary humility, and worſhipping of Angels,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Rev. 19. 10. &amp; 22. 9.—<hi>And I fell at his feet and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him, and he ſaid unto me, ſee thou do it not: I am thy fellow-ſervant, and of thy Brethren that have the Teſtimony of Jeſus: Worſhip God,</hi> &amp;c.—And certainly, if we muſt not Worſhip an Angel if we ſhou'd ſee him, I know not which way it can be prov'd lawful to intrude into thoſe things which we have not ſeen, as the Apoſtle ſays of them that Worſhip Angels, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 18. I can find no Text of Scripture for it; but you ſee, Madam, how many I have produc'd againſt it. And I believe we ſhall ſee as little reaſon to pray to Saints and Angels, as to worſhip 'em.</p>
            <p>Iſai. 63. 16.—<hi>Doubtleſs thou art our Father, tho'</hi> Abraham <hi>be ignorant of us, and tho'</hi> Iſrael <hi>acknowledge us not; thou, O Lord, art our Father, our Redeemer, thy Name is from Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</hi>—Where be pleas'd to obſerve, that, if it was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to pray to, and in ſo doing to worſhip Saints departed, why might not the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> have made them Images of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and pray'd to them to help 'em in time of trouble; or, to put the beſt face upon it, that they wou'd pray to God for their own Offspring on Earth, as well as they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have their Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives of, and Prayers to their Saints; who for the moſt part, we are apt to believe, are only titular ones? They knew this wou'd be to no purpoſe, for <hi>Abraham</hi> was ignorant of 'em, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> acknowledged them not. But,</p>
            <p>Jer. 15. 1.—<hi>Then ſaid the Lord unto me, Tho'</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Samuel <hi>ſtood before me, yet, my mind cou'd not be toward this People.</hi>—That is, If it was poſſible for <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> whoſe Prayers were ſo prevalent with me when they liv'd on Earth, to interceed for this People now, yet my Mind cou'd not be toward them. Thus then appears the Vanity of invocating Saints departed, in that <hi>the Dead know nothing,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56476:26"/> neither have they any more a portion for ever of any thing that is done under the Sun,</hi> Eccl. 9. 5, 6. But whether Angels and Saints departed, are acquainted with our Condition, or can hear our Prayers, is not much to the purpoſe; 'tis enough to tell you, that, ſuppoſing they are endued with ſuch Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, our Worſhipping them wou'd detract from the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, which he has ſaid he will not give to another: and our invocating them wou'd make them Mediators and Interceſſors, when the Apoſtle plainly affirms, That <hi>there is but one Mediator between God and man, the man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 5.</p>
            <p>To conclude this, becauſe I wou'd be as brief as poſſibly I may, I ſhall refer you to the Fourth Chapter of <hi>Deutero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy,</hi> where you'll find, the great Reaſon that <hi>Moſes</hi> gives the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> why they ſhou'd not make 'em Images, is, becauſe when they heard the Voice of the Lord from the Mountain, they ſaw no Similitude; which he ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges more than once. And then, what Grounds can they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> pretend, for expoſing a Picture of him, who always was Inviſible? This has been lately acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd to be Idolatry, by one that writ more for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in this particular, than, as he ſaid afterwards, he intended, tho' all little enough to the purpoſe: or at leaſt more was added, by ſome-body elſe, to what he did; as may be conjectur'd from the variation of the Style: but no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which. <q>The Author makes Idolatry of two Sorts; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reaſons for abrogating the Teſt,</hi> p. 128.</note> The firſt whereof is, the Worſhipping any Image or Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols of falſe Gods, as the Supreme Deities: and ſays, If they do not this, then they are innocent of the worſt part of Idolatry. The ſecond is, the making, or, as he ſays, the attempting to make a Similitude of the true God, or uncreated Divine Nature. That, ſays he, is the other part of Idolatry, and the Scripture knows no more; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore however Superſtitious they may be in their uſe of Images, yet they cannot be guilty of Idolatry, but upon one of theſe two accounts, (I ſuppoſe he means, the bare
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:56476:27"/> uſe of Images in the Worſhip of God was none, becauſe he ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 124, that God was ſo far from forbidding the uſe of Images in his Worſhip, that he wou'd not be Worſhipp'd without them.) And he ſays, that no Man was ever ſo hardy as to charge either of theſe two Kinds of Idolatry upon that Church.</q> But, not to enquire whether their Worſhipping God by an Image, which he ſeems to Vindicate in another <note place="margin">P. 126.</note> place, be the making a Similitude of the true God, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created Divine Nature; I aſſure you, Madam, I have ſeen the Ancient of Days pictur'd like an Old Man, with a great Beard, by which they repreſented the Unity of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head: And in another place, the Trinity of Perſons, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on a row in a Sheet held up by two Angels; two of the three, <hi>viz.</hi> The Father and the Holy Ghoſt, with their Backs toward me, to expreſs their Inviſibility, tho' in the other Picture I had ſeen God face to face: and the Son in the middle, as the ſecond Perſons place, with his face viſible. Now in my opinion, one or both of theſe Repreſentations muſt be Idolatry by their own confeſſion. But the preſent Circumſtances of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church are ſuch, that if they can't make People believe they Practiſe no ſuch things as theſe, they'll do little good on thoſe of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> and 'tis to be hoped they'll get but little ground that way, while there are any left to diſcover their Forgeries.</p>
            <p>No more Authority have they for invocating Saints and Angels, than for Worſhipping Images. The only Preſident, as I know of, in the Primitive Times, was the voluntary Humility of the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> condemn'd by St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. But for theſe they muſt have recourſe to the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made to doating Women, and the Viſions of mad <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcans,</hi> and I know not whom—That <hi>Raphael</hi> ſhou'd be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocated on a Journey, and againſt Diſeaſes in general; but in particular, <hi>Apollonia</hi> againſt the Tooth-ach; <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> and <hi>Roch,</hi> againſt the Plague; St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> againſt Tempeſts; <hi>Michael</hi> and St. <hi>George,</hi> againſt Enemies. From whom, if <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Serrar.</hi> lit. 2. q. 32.</note> they be invocated particularly, ſay they, Experience and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:56476:27"/> Tradition have diſcover'd ſpecial help in theſe Caſes. But what is this, but the ancient Heathen Idolatry, reviv'd in the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Which is ſo much the worſe there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity; and Men that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to know the true God, blaſphemouſly imagin, or aſſert againſt their Conſciences, which I think the worſe of the two, That help to come from the Creature, which can only come from the Creator. May not we on better Grounds deiſy our Phyſicians? But theſe things they'll venture to deny, tho' they are eaſily prov'd: that which they chiefly acknowledge in this Point, is their praying to Saints and Angels to pray for them, or as ſome ſay, to pray to Chriſt to interceed for them, it being arrogant Preſumption, for Mortals to go to Chriſt immediately. But this is down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>Gnoſticiſm;</hi> and we of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> have our Saviour's own words for our Encouragement, if they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have not, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 6, <hi>I am the way, the truth and the life: no man cometh to the Father but by me.</hi> And we know of no other Interceſſor in Heaven, but Chriſt. Therefore I think it a privation of our Chriſtian Liberty, to debar us from Praying to him immediately, on Pretence of too much Preſumption in ſo doing; for he himſelf invites all that labour and are heavy laden, to come to him, and he will give 'em reſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 28. He does not ſay, <hi>Come to me</hi> by my Mother, or by St. <hi>Michael,</hi> or St. <hi>Bennet,</hi> &amp;c. But, <hi>Come to me</hi>—directly.</p>
            <p>5. The Fifth Enquiry muſt be, <hi>Whether there is any ſuch Place as Purgatory?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as they have been manag'd, are moſt of 'em ſo order'd, as to be as ſuitable and conformable to the temper of Humane Nature as they well may be: as might be made appear, if we had time, in theſe already ſpoken to. But above all, the Doctrine of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, is as obliging and complaiſant to Fleſh and Blood, as any thing can be. For this takes off all neceſſity of a ſtrict and reſtrain'd life; here needs no mortifying our Members
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:56476:28"/> which are upon the Earth, as the Apoſtle's advice was: Men need not be ſo fearful of pleaſing their Appetites, as they ſhould be, if they were to follow the rigid Precepts of our Saviour, or St. <hi>Paul.</hi> But the <hi>Epicuroean</hi> Principle will make a Man happy here, in gratifying the Luſts of the Fleſh; and hereafter he ſhall be happy in Heaven too, if he has but been ſo frugal as to ſave a little Money to pay for a Catholick Burial, only undergoing a little Frixation or Roaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the way. That this is the genuine Explication of the Doctrine of Purgatory, as it is receiv'd and propagated in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, might be made appear by many good Conſequences, if I had time, and it was worth the Pains to conſider every Particular. But 'tis done at large already by an Excellent Hand; and the Buſineſs of the preſent Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Stil. <hi>Idol. of the Church of</hi> Rome.</note> is not ſo much to that, as to Enquire whether there is any ſuch Place as Purgatory or no?</p>
            <p>There are but two Texts in the New Teſtament that can with any colour be urg'd to this purpoſe. One is, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 19. where 'tis ſaid, that Chriſt <hi>went and Preach'd to the Spirits in Priſon.</hi> And the other, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 15, <hi>If any mans works ſhall be burnt, he ſhall ſuffer loſs: but he himſelf ſhall be ſaved, yet ſo, as by fire.</hi> On theſe two Texts this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is built. If therefore I can make it plain, that neither of theſe Texts are to the purpoſe, I think I ſhall have little more to do than to deny the Doctrine to be true; foraſmuch as in any Matter of Diſpute the Affirmative ought to be prov'd before the Negative. I begin then with the firſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 19.</p>
            <p>In the foregoing Verſe, the Apoſtle tells us, that Chriſt hath once ſuffer'd for ſins, the juſt for the unjuſt, (that he might bring us to God) being put to death in the fleſh, but quicken'd by the ſpirit. And then adds, By which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he went and preach'd to the ſpirits in Priſon. From whence moſt Expoſitors gather, that what our Saviour is ſaid to do here, he did after his Reſurrection: As if the Apoſtle had ſaid, He was put to Death in the Fleſh, but
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:56476:28"/> was quicken'd, or rais'd again by the Spirit; and after that, he went by the ſame Spirit, or Power, that quicken'd him, and Preach'd to the Spirits in Priſon. And that the word Priſon, here, can't mean Purgatory, will more plainly appear, if we follow the Apoſtle as he goes on—<hi>By which alſo he went and Preach'd to the Spirits in Priſon; which ſometime were Diſobedient, when once the long ſuffering of God waited in the Days of</hi> Noah, <hi>while the Ark was preparing: wherein few, that is, Eight Perſons were ſaved by Water.</hi> The like Figure where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, even Baptiſm doth alſo now ſave us, by the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We read, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 3. that God ſaid, <hi>My Spirit ſhall not always ſtrive with Man, for that he alſo is Fleſh: yet his Days ſhall be an Hundred and Twenty Years.</hi> The Deluge was determin'd for the Sins of the Old World; yet God of his Mercy wou'd give 'em ſo long time as One Hundred and Twenty Years to Repent in; and ſent <hi>Noah</hi> to Preach Repentance, and Threaten Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to all that wou'd not amend their Lives. Whence this of the Apoſtle has been interpreted of Chriſt's Preaching the Goſpel to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> by his Apoſtles, after his Reſurrection when he had ſent his Spirit among 'em. And ſo, thoſe that wou'd not repent at the Preaching of the Goſpel, ſhou'd one Day periſh by Fire, as they of the Old World did by Water, for not Repenting at the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Noah:</hi> For as Chriſt was then reveal'd in a flood of Water, ſo he will again be revealed in flaming Fire to take Vengeance on them that obey not his Goſpel. But they that wou'd repent, and be obedient to his Goſpel, ſhou'd be ſaved by Baptiſm, as <hi>Noah</hi> was in the Ark: yet not merely from a Temporal Puniſhment, but from Everlaſting Deſtruction. Now, to make the Priſon here ſpoken of, Purgatory; is to ſay, in effect, that thoſe that were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd by the Deluge of the Old World, have remain'd ever ſince in this Purgatory 'till our Saviour's Crucifixion, and that in one of the Three Days in which he lay in the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:56476:29"/> Grave, he went and Preach'd the Goſpel of Repentance to them. But this can't be made deducble from the words of the Apoſtle, but rather the contrary. For, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which we render, Priſon; ſignifies any kind of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle whatever, a Sheath for a Sword, as well as a Gaol for Priſoners, and as properly the Body of a Man, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Soul is kept, as any thing elſe: any thing containing, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Priſon, in reference to the thing contain'd. So that Chriſt's Preaching to the Spirits in Priſon, here, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but either the Preaching of <hi>Noah</hi> to thoſe of the Old World, or of his Apoſtles to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> of the New, whoſe Souls were penn'd up in their Bodies, which were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd in Filthy Luſts, as uſeleſs as a Sword is while it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in the Sheath. And this is the ſence that the beſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors put upon the place. <hi>Beza</hi> eſpecially, is very copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and fully diſcuſſes the point, proving that this Priſon can in no wiſe be taken for Purgatory. But the Reverend Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> has moſt ingenuouſly and accurately expreſs'd the Apoſtles meaning; and therefore with his words I ſhall conclude,—<q>Chriſt, ſays he, is an Example of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for well-doing, in his Dying for Sins, not his own but ours, he being righteous died for us who were unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, (that when we were Aliens and Enemies to God, he might reconcile us to him, and give us Authority to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach him,) wherein yet for our example and comfort it muſt be obſerv'd, that tho' as a Man cloath'd in our Fleſh, he was put to Death, and that innocently, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe Redemption for us, yet by the power of God in him he was moſt gloriouſly rais'd from the Dead, and ſhall conſequently, by raiſing and reſcuing us out of the preſent Sufferings, and deſtroying all obdurate Sinners, ſhew forth wonderful Evidences of Power and Life: The very ſame in effect that of old he did at the time in which, beyond all others, he ſhew'd himſelf in Power and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty againſt his Enemies, but withal in great Mercy and Deliverance to his Obedient Servants that adher'd to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:56476:29"/> him: I mean in the Days of the Old World, when by <hi>Noah,</hi> that Preacher of Righteouſneſs, he gave thoſe treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able warnings to thoſe that made no uſe of the Light of Nature in their Hearts, to the Spirits or Souls of thoſe that were then alive before the Flood, which God had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them with impreſſions of Good and Evil, but through their cuſtoms of Sin were as a Sword put up in a Sheath, laid up in their Bodies unprofitably.—</q>So then, upon the whole matter, whether the ſence of the Apoſtle be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to our Saviours Preaching, by <hi>Noah,</hi> to them of the Old World, or by his Apoſtles to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> of the New, is not much to the purpoſe; this is the plain reſolution of the preſent Quere, That the word <hi>Priſon</hi> here made uſe of, is only a Metaphorical Epithet given to the Body in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Soul, a Compariſon made of the Soul con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd in the Body of a ſinful Man, with a Man lock'd up in a Priſon, And thus when our Saviour, by his Miniſters, Preaches the Goſpel, eſpecially to Unbelievers or Wicked Men, he may be ſaid to Preach to Spirits in Priſon. From what has been ſaid then, I think Purgatory can't be aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the words of St. <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence we come to conſider thoſe of St. <hi>Paul, If any Man's Work ſhall be burnt, he ſhall ſuffer loſs, but he himſelf ſhall be ſaved, yet ſo, as by Fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle, <hi>Verſe</hi> 10, ſays, <hi>According to the Grace of God which was given to me, as a wiſe Maſter-Builder I have laid the Foundation, and another buildeth thereon:</hi> And, <hi>Verſe</hi> 12. he ſpeaks of Two ſorts of Men that build on this Foundation; Firſt, <hi>thoſe that build thereon Gold, Silver and Precious-Stones:</hi> and Secondly, <hi>thoſe that build thereon Wood, Hay and Stubble. Now,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Verſe</hi> 13, <hi>Every Man's Work ſhall be made manifeſt. For the Day ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, becauſe it ſhall be reveal'd by Fire, and the Fire ſhall try every Man's Work, of what ſort it is. And,</hi> as he goes on, <hi>If any Man's Work ſhall abide which he hath built thereon, he ſhall receive a Reward. But if any Man's Work
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:56476:30"/> ſhall be burnt, he ſhall ſuffer loſs,</hi> &amp;c. Which may be thus explain'd.</p>
            <p>There were among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> when the Apoſtle writ this Epiſtle to 'em, two ſorts of Preachers; ſome, who endeavour'd nothing more, than to Preach the pure ſimplicity of the Goſpel, and to feed the Flock of Chriſt with ſound and wholſome Doctrine: And others, who pretended to greater parts and knowledge than other Men; and theſe with ſuperfluous flouriſhes and empty gloſſes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to win the Hearts of their Hearers by their worldly wiſdom, as the Apoſtle calls it. As the other ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died for the preſervation of a Good Conſcience in the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſcharge of their Duty, ſo theſe made it their chief care to become the Peoples Favourites, by being as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant and obliging as they cou'd, and by Indulging 'em in ſome petty matters, as they call'd 'em, that the Goſpel might not ſeem too heavy a burden to 'em. They wou'd tell the People of Works of Supererogation, ſome things they might do more than they were commanded to do; and ſo brought in worſhipping of Angels under a pretence of voluntary Humility, intruding into thoſe things which they had not ſeen, being vainly puffed up with their fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minds, as the Apoſtle teſtifies, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 18. And by ſuch little tricks as theſe they gain'd more and more upon the giddy Affections of the multitude, 'till at laſt they broke out into that Diviſion which call'd for this Epiſtle. Things being at this paſs, the Apoſtle thought it high time to think of a way, if poſſible, to put a ſtop to thoſe Enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities which were ſo faſt breaking into the Church. And to this end, he firſt mildly reproves the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> for their overmuch curioſity, and affection of Speculation, rather than wholſome Doctrine. And then heproceeds to ſhew 'em the vanity of ſuch Speculative Preachers, by tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 'em, that he had laid the Foundation, and that no Man cou'd lay another than what was laid already, which was Jeſus Chriſt. Now, ſays he, <hi>If any Man builds upon
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:56476:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> this Foundation, Gold, Silver, Precious-Stones, Wood, Hay, or Stubble? Every Man's Work ſhall be made manifeſt. For the Day ſhall declare it, becauſe it ſhall be reveal'd by Fire, and the Fire ſhall try every Man's Work, of what ſort it is. And if any Man's Work ſhall abide, which he hath built upon that Foundation which he had laid, he ſhall receive a Reward.</hi> That is, He that ſhall approve himſelf a ſincere Preacher of the Goſpel, that he has fed the Flock of Chriſt with ſound and profitable Doctrine, he ſhall in the Day of Trial have this to comfort him againſt all Temporal Calamities, That he has Acted as a faithful Paſtor ought to do, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though Tribulations beſet him on all ſides, yet he is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain he whom he has ſerv'd is faithful, and will undoubtedly perform his promiſe to his faithful Servants, ſo that in the midſt of the greateſt Afflictions he's ſure to become more than a Conqueror, and as ſuch ſhall not miſs of a moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Reward. But, <hi>If any Man's Work ſhall be burnt, he ſhall ſuffer loſs:</hi> That is, He ſhall in the Day of Trial be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of the invalidity and unprofitableneſs of his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which will cauſe in him the pains of a guilty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which commonly attend on thoſe that have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable in their Stations; and the loſs of his former credit, will cauſe him ſhame, and a deteſtation of thoſe vain and empty Opinions, which before he ſo earneſtly defended; and all theſe together will put him in danger of loſing his reward hereafter. Yet notwithſtanding all this, tho' his fleſhy opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are conſum'd and brought to nothing, if he has been ſo fortunate as to hold to the Foundation in the main Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Chriſtianity, he himſelf may be ſaved, but 'twill be ſo hardly, as by Fire. That is, tho' he had been infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with <hi>Gnoſticiſm,</hi> if he did not proceed ſo far as actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to deny Chriſt the Foundation, as his Doctrine before was that he might in caſe of Perſecution, yet his not deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him at laſt, is an Abnegation of that Doctrine as Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, and on that account he might be ſaved, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the unprofitableneſs of his Preaching otherwiſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:56476:31"/> ſimply conſider'd, but it wou'd be ſo hardly, as when one with the greateſt difficulty frees himſelf from the fury of a devouring Fire. I ſuppoſe the Apoſtles meaning may be to this purpoſe; that That Preacher who takes more delight in diſcuſſing Points of Controverſy, and the nice Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of School-Diſputes, than in Preaching the Goſpel ſo as it may beſt edify the generality of People that come to hear him; If to this he adds ſome ſuperfluous Doctrines of his own, provided they be not Heretical, but he ſtill holds the Foundation, yet all this may not damn him, if he does not at laſt deny Chriſt, but tho' his Works in the day of Trial ſhall prove but empty Chimera's, the vain Fancies of his own Brain, Wood and Stubble built upon the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel, and as ſuch ſhall inſtantly be conſumed, yet he himſelf may eſcape the deſerved Puniſhment of an Unprofitable Preacher, but 'twill be, as a man whoſe Houſe is on fire round about him, and all his Subſtance being burnt, he himſelf with great hazard of his Life eſcapes the Flames. For 'tis not to be thought that every petty Error incurs Damnation if it is not of Faith; for thus the Holy Fathers of the Church in all Ages have fail'd, yet their failings not thought damnable, ſo long as in all things neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation they held to the Foundation. But the queſtion is, Whether according to the ſence of the Apoſtle, ſuch Men muſt be ſaved by the fire of Purgatory? St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells us that, <hi>Both good and bad, thoſe on the right hand as well as thoſe on the left, muſt be tried by this Fire the Apoſtle ſpeaks of.</hi> And a little after, <hi>This Fire,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is to be underſtood as ſuch, through which both muſt paſs, They that build Gold, as well as thoſe that build Wood.</hi> And will any ſay that St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles paſs'd through Purgatory? Or will any of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> aſſert this thing of their Seraphic St. <hi>Francis,</hi> St. <hi>Dominic,</hi> or their ever famous <hi>Loyola?</hi> 'Tis plain, the Apoſtle here ſpeaks Metaphorically; he makes a Fire wherein a man is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Burning, a Similitude of the danger thoſe <hi>Gnoſticks</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:56476:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> were in by building their vain and unprofitable Doctrines upon the Foundation which he had laid: So that upon the whole, I think the beſt way to explain a figurative Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is by a figurative Suppoſition. Let us therefore ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Foundation of Stone laid by ſome famous Builder: Two men take this Foundation whereon to Build 'em Houſes to live in; one of the two Builds his Houſe, we'll ſuppoſe of Gold and Silver, as the Apoſtle expreſſes it, but very plain and homely, after the rude <hi>Gothic</hi> way of Building, no way charming or delightful outwardly. The other makes uſe of no other Materials but Wood and Straw, but alarms the World with his curious Carving, and fine Devices, after the beautiful <hi>Corinthian</hi> Order, Stately and Magnificent, to Charm all that ſhall look on it, and ſo finiſhes a delicate Piece of Work. Now the common Vanity of the World is ſuch, that Men are generally apt to part with all to pleaſe their Fancies; and ſo it is here, the Multitude ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire his Building, and cry up the Workman almoſt to Adoration, and tho' his next Neighbour's Houſe is built of Gold and Silver, yet 'tis a plain homely thing, rough and old faſhion'd, not worth taking notice of or looking on. But here, the Ingenuity and Art of the Workman, the ſingular contrivance of every part, the joint and apt connection and ſuitableneſs of the whole, the juſt Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum and Harmony every where viſible, the regularity of the Columns ſo adorn'd with all ſorts of delightful Carv'd works, Fruits and Flowers; and, in a word, the whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick is ſo noble, and in all reſpects outwardly perfect, that 'tis preferrable to all the Gold and Silver of the Univerſe. But now comes the day of Trial, when the Fire muſt try both theſe mens works, of what ſort they are. The Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation being Stone, the Fire paſſes on to the Building; And by reaſon of the firſt man's Houſe being built with Gold and Silver, which the Fire cannot reduce into it ſelf, That eſcapes untouch'd, only as there might poſſibly be a droſſy ſubſtance on the outſide, the Fire licks off that, and ſo, all
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:56476:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> the alteration it makes there, is, when that droſs is conſum'd the Houſe appears much more ſplendid and glorious, as the Metal is more refin'd, and purify'd by the Fire. But the condition of the other fine Building, is quite contrary; for, conſiſting chiefly of Wood and Straw, and ſuch combuſtible Matter, it preſently takes fire, and burns furiouſly, that the Poor man, who is ſuddenly ſurpriz'd with the Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, being perhaps two or three Stories high, and the Flames aſcending, and threatning Deſtruction round about him, knows of no way whereby to eſcape one danger, but by running into another: And delays in ſuch caſes being dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, he looks out at his Window, and, not conſidering the greatneſs of the fall, his fear of Burning being much greater, he at the hazard of his Life, endeavours to ſave it, by leaping down into the Street; whence, if he ſo eſcapes, he becomes a miſerable Spectator of the Ruin of that, which but Yeſterday was the Worlds wonder: and they that were before ſo taken with it, now ſee it reduc'd to Aſhes, while the other Houſe which before they thought ſo deſpicable, ſhines in their Imaginations as the Sun in the Firmament. This I take to be as lively a repreſentation of the ſence of the Text, as the words will bear: and then I leave to any reaſonable Perſon to judge if the Apoſtle here ſpeaks of any ſuch place as Purgatory. I dare ſay, St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> had no ſuch thoughts; for repeating the ſame words, <hi>But he ſhall be ſaved, yet ſo as by Fire;</hi> 
               <q>That is, ſays he, as a man that, when at Midnight his Houſe is ſet on Fire, wakes and leaps out of Bed, and runs Naked out of Doors, taking nothing along with him, his only care being to free his own Body from the Flames.</q> But the Gentlemen we are to deal with in theſe days are mere Grammatiſts where they can find any thing in the Letter that ſeems to favour their purpoſe, though the ſence of the Text may be hid in a Figure. But he that can aſſert the Doctrine of Purgatory from ſuch a Text as this, may as well ſay that the Apoſtle was a Maſon or Carpenter, becauſe he calls himſelf <hi>a Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:56476:32"/> or that he Preach'd to Houſes and Walls, becauſe he calls the <hi>Corinthians</hi> God's <hi>Building;</hi> or that our Saviour himſelf was a Stone, becauſe he is expreſly call'd <hi>the head ſtone of the corner.</hi> But whither wou'd ſuch abſurdities hurry us? I aſſure you, Madam, 'tis very unreaſonable to ſuppoſe the Doctrine from ſuch a Text as this; and I think they can find none plainer than one of theſe two. Which being made thus plain to the contrary, I ſhall only briefly hint a few Texts againſt the particular Doctrine of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and ſo conclude this Point.</p>
            <p>Eccl. 11. 3.—<hi>If the clouds be full of rain, they empty them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the Earth: and if the tree fall toward the South, or toward the North: in the place where the tree falleth, there it ſhall lie.</hi>—This Text is a Metaphorical intimation of the ſtate of the Soul after this life. As a Tree that is falling muſt fall one way, either <hi>to the South or to the North,</hi> &amp;c.; So the Soul when it leaves the Body muſt go to ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain place: and as the Tree ſhall remain in the place where it fell, ſo the Soul muſt abide in the place whither ſhe firſt goes when ſhe leaves the Body. But the Preacher is more plain to the purpoſe, <hi>Chap.</hi> 12. 7. where he ſays, <hi>The Duſt,</hi> that is, Man's Body, <hi>ſhall return to the Earth as it was; and the Spirit ſhall return to God who gave it.</hi> And the Prophet ſays, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 57. 3. <hi>The Righteous ſhall enter into Peace.</hi>—Now according to the Practice of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in this particular, unleſs the ſpecial favour of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> intervene, all, both good and bad, muſt paſs through Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, in order to their Perfection, tho' according to the Doctrine of the firſt Query, they may be more than per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect before they come thither. But what then becomes of the many Promiſes made to the Godly, both in the Old and New Teſtaments, if before they can enjoy the Rewards promis'd, they muſt undergo ſo ſevere a Puniſhment by the way?</p>
            <p>Revel. 14. 13.—<hi>And I heard a voice from Heaven, ſaying unto me, write, Bleſſed are the Dead which die in the Lord,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:56476:33"/> from henceforth</hi>—And, if there is any ſuch place as Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, wherein the beſt of Men muſt endure Torment for a Time, how can the Blood of Chriſt be ſaid to <hi>cleanſe any from all Sin,</hi> 1 Joh. 1. 7? Certainly, God does not require that his Servants ſhou'd paſs through the Fire to purify 'em and make 'em fit for Heaven, after they are waſh'd in the Blood of his Son. We are taught by the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 14, that the Blood of Chriſt purges our Conſciences from dead Works: but we quite deſtroy the belief of this, if we admit the leaſt thought of any other Purgation. Our Saviour tells us, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 18. that <hi>He that believeth on him is not condemned.</hi> And if God does not condemn, 'tis hard to think he'll pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh: which he muſt do, if the beſt of Men muſt paſs through Purgatory before they can come to Heaven. But we can meet with no ſuch place in the Scriptures. We find but two ways mention'd, a <hi>narrow</hi> and a <hi>broad;</hi> a <hi>ſtrait gate</hi> and a <hi>wide,</hi> into one of which we muſt enter. And the Apoſtle ſays expreſly, <hi>All ſhall appear before the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſeat of Chriſt, there to receive according to what we have done in the Body:</hi> and then certainly, if there is any ſuch place as Purgatory, God muſt be thought unjuſt in calling Men to account for their Sins when they are purg'd from 'em. But 'tis much ſafer to believe there is no ſuch place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Virgil</hi> indeed tells us of ſome ſuch kind of place in the Sixth Book of his <hi>Aeneas,</hi> in his Account of <hi>Aeneas</hi>'s Progreſs into the infernal World to viſit his Father. <q>When he came to the <hi>Stygian</hi> ſhore, he ſaw Old <hi>Charon</hi> about his wonted Bus'neſs, plying the Oars to carry ſuch over as came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Paſſage. But he ſaw ſome miſerable Ghoſts on the Banks and in dark Woods thereabouts, to whom the old Ferry-man was very ſurly, and deny'd 'em Paſſage, tho' without doubt they'd have paid him as well for his pains as others did. <hi>Aeneas,</hi> as we may ſuppoſe, was amaz'd at this partiality, and ask'd his Guide, <hi>What was the meaning of</hi> Charon'<hi>s rough behaviour to thoſe poor Souls?</hi> To which
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56476:33"/> ſhe anſwers, <hi>Thoſe you ſee him take into his Boat are buried, and by that means challenge his Service; But thoſe he beats away, are not. None muſt paſs theſe Streams 'till the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of their Funeral are perform'd; but they muſt abide in theſe diſmal Shades on this ſide the River an Hundred years, unleſs they are buried ſooner, and then, I ſuppoſe buried or not buried, they obtain their Paſſage.</hi> Then the Poet ſets down a Dialogue between <hi>Aeneas</hi> and his old Pilot <hi>Palinurus,</hi> who being unfortunately caſt away, was kill'd in <hi>Italy;</hi> and by the cruel Murtherers left unburied: for which reaſon he muſt be confin'd to this Purgatory, 'till thoſe People, mov'd by Prodigious Omnes, ſhou'd Solemnize his Funeral.</q> Now not to make a Parallel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this Fiction of the Poet, and the Purgatory of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I ſhall only tell you, that, I have ſeen the place repreſented by them of that Church, not much unlike it. They have a River, in which many are plung'd up to the Neck, and labouring very hard to get out, at one ſide of the River is Hell's mouth open, to terrifie the poor Souls, and over their heads, Heaven for their Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Whether they intend this River for <hi>Styx</hi> or <hi>Acheron,</hi> is not to the purpoſe; 'tis enough to ſuppoſe the Doctrine of Purgatory very ancient; becauſe in vogue with the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Romans</hi> before Chriſt's coming into the World: tho' of late years it has got a Name which it wanted before, and as it was formerly known by the <hi>Stygian ſhore, Black ſhades,</hi> &amp;c. now Purgatory is the Proper name of the place, and is therefore deſervedly written with a Capital P.</p>
            <p>6. The Sixth Enquiry propoſed was, <hi>Whether the Maſs is a Sacrifice for the Quick and Dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Doctrine is built upon the other of Purgatory, and 'tis to be deliver'd from that place that Men are ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to trade for Maſſes and Indulgences: which has added ſo much to the Revenue of the Church, that it can now very hardly be laid aſide.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:56476:34"/>
            <p>But I have often thought it ſtrange, that Men profeſſing Chriſtianity, ſhou'd be ſo far bewitch'd to Gain as to deny the Efficacy of Chriſt's Sufferings. For if Indulgences will make amends for Sin, and the Maſs atone for unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, what becomes of the All-ſufficiency of Chriſt's Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, the Satisfaction made by his Death? What need have Men to go ſo far about for Mercy and Forgiveneſs, when they may have it nearer home? Here's a Merchant has In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences to ſell at reaſonable Rates, by virtue of which a Man may gratifie the Luſts of his Fleſh here, and when he Dies, a ſmall Matter towards Building or Repairing ſome religious Conventicle, will purchaſe Maſſes enough to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him out of Purgatory; and then let any judge if ſuch a Man is not far wiſer than a ſneaking Heretick, who lives in ignorance of theſe Catholick Helps and Salvo's. But for all that, if we may be allow'd to believe the Scriptures, we have no ſuch by-ways to Heaven; the way that leads thither is <hi>ſtrait</hi> as well as <hi>narrow.</hi> So then, let others truſt to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, and ſo be cheated of their Souls and Money too, while we tread in the Path which is made plain before us; and tho' we may want a little Elbow-room, yet tis better travelling ſo in a clean and ſafe way, than, by rambling out of it for more liberty, to truſt to the Promiſe of a falſe Guide that we ſhall come into it again, and ſo follow him through Boggs and Rivers in danger of Drowning every ſtep of the way. 'Tis evident enough, that the Son of God is our only Sacrifice; for the Apoſtle ſays, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. 7, <hi>Chriſt our Paſſover is ſacrificed for us:</hi> And the Scriptures ſufficiently teſtifie, that by one Oblation of himſelf once offer'd, he made ſufficient Satisfaction for the Sins of the whole World. And then what need have we of farther Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices? nay, what warrant can be brought from the Word of God, to juſtifie the Sacrifice of the Maſs, which is the only new one contended for? The Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 1, Exhorts us to <hi>preſent our Bodies a living Sacrifice, holy, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto God, as our reaſonable Service.</hi> Which Text <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:56476:34"/> thinks ſufficient to the purpoſe, and thus he argues: <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is a Sacrifice properly ſo call'd, that is, an External Oblation, made only to God, wherein by a lawful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, ſome ſenſible Subſtance is by Myſtical rites conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, and ſo chang'd, or, in reference to what it was before, deſtroy'd. But Chriſtians have no ſuch Sacrifice to offer to God, but the Maſs. Neither are the <hi>Romans</hi> here commanded to Kill themſelves; for that wou'd be an heinous Sin. Therefore the Maſs muſt be the Sacrifice here ſpoken of. And farther <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is the word here uſed by the Apoſtle, is that Sacrifice which is offer'd by a lawful Miniſter. But no Sacrifice is among Chriſtians offer'd by the Miniſter, but the Maſs. Therefore the Maſs is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or a proper Sacrifice.</q> Now not to ſay the Maſs is no ſenſible Subſtance, which he makes the main condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Sacrifice, I ſhall at preſent thus examine the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Apoſtle does not ſpeak here of the office of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, but the Duty of the Miniſters and People both. All are to preſent their Bodies a living Sacrifice. <hi>I beſeech you therefore, Brethren,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Therefore ſuppoſing the Maſs was a ſenſible Subſtance, yet the Apoſtle can't intend that, becauſe that is to be offer'd by the Miniſter only.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Granting all he wou'd have in reference to the Maſs's being a Sacrifice, yet the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is as properly us'd by the Apoſtle in reference to the Sacrifice of a Man's Body, as of the Maſs: For 'tis confeſs'd that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is an Oblation made to God only, wherein ſome ſenſible Subſtance is by myſtical Rites conſecrated, and ſo chang'd, or, in reference to what it was before, deſtroy'd. Accordingly, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle adviſes us to preſent our Bodies <hi>a living Sacrifice unto God;</hi> and in the next Verſe, <hi>Be not conformed to this World:</hi> where, by our renouncing the World, we conſecrate our Bodies to God's Service, and ſo, as the Apoſtle farther ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts us, we are transform'd or chang'd by the renewing of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:56476:35"/> our Mind, and our Bodies in reference to what they were before, corrupted and polluted by Sin, are deſtroy'd.</p>
            <p n="4">4. So then the Apoſtle here makes uſe of a Metaphor to expreſs a reaſonable Duty; as a Sacrifice is laid on the Altar, kill'd and cut in pieces, ſo we muſt die to ſin, and mortifie our Members which are upon the Earth, cut off all Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to this World keep our Bodies under, and bring 'em into ſubjection to the Will of God, and ſo being transformed from what we were before, Servants and Sacrifices to Sin, we become holy Sacrifices and acceptable to God. Whence,</p>
            <p n="5">5. Let us enquire what are the proper Sacrifices of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, becauſe he ſays, that they have no other but the Maſs. St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 Ep. c. 2. v. 5, ſays, we as <hi>lively Stones, are built upon a ſpiritual houſe, an holy Prieſthood, to offer up ſpiritual Sacrifices, acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And what thoſe ſpiritual Sacrifices are, we may be inform'd by other places of Scripture. The Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. 5. adviſes us <hi>to offer to God the Sacrifices of Righteouſneſs.</hi> And, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 23, <hi>Whoſo offereth Praiſe, glorifieth God.</hi> And, 51. 17, 19, <hi>The Sacrifices of God are a broken Spirit:</hi> and, <hi>the Lord will be pleas'd with Sacrifices of Righteouſneſs.</hi> And, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141. 2, <hi>Let my Prayer be ſet before thee as Incenſe; and the lifting up of my hands, as the evening Sacrifice.</hi> Theſe are great Expreſſions from one under the Law, when the Morning and Evening Sacrifices were ſo abſolutely neceſſary. But what have we from thoſe that were under the Goſpel? Our Bleſſed Saviour of right challenges the firſt place, who in his own Perſon, blames the Phariſees for not knowing the meaning of this, <hi>I will have Mercy and not Sacrifice,</hi> Matth. 12. 7. The Apoſtle is very plain, to the purpoſe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 15, &amp;c. <hi>Now ye</hi> Philippians <hi>know alſo, that in the beginning of the Goſpel, when I departed from</hi> Macedonia, <hi>no Church communicated with me, as concerning giving and receiving, but ye only. For even in</hi> Theſſalonica <hi>ye ſent once and again unto my neceſſity. Not becauſe I deſire a gift: but I deſire fruit that may abound to your account. But I have all, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:56476:35"/> abound: I am full, having receiv'd of</hi> Epaphroditus <hi>the things which were ſent from you, an Odour of a ſweet ſmell, a Sacrifice acceptable, well-pleaſing to God.</hi> From all which, the Sacrifices of Chriſtians are Mercy, Alms-Deeds, Prayer, Praiſe, Contrition, and all Chriſtian Duties. And theſe are the Sacrifices which are to be offer'd up to God, by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry living Chriſtian for himſelf. But I can find no ſuch Sacrifice as the Maſs, nor indeed any other than thoſe above-mention'd. For Chriſt Jeſus is the Sacrifice for all Chriſtians in general, and theſe are Sacrifices which every Chriſtian muſt offer to God for himſelf in particular. And thus I have briefly given my Opinion of the Maſs, which amounts to this in the general, that Chriſt being our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice and Propitiation, we have no reaſon to think of any other; and he having offer'd himſelf once to God for all, there can be no other Offerings needful, but ſuch as every Man muſt offer for himſelf, <hi>the Sacrifice of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi> And as the Maſs is not a Sacrifice for the Living, neither can it be ſuppos'd a Sacrifice for the Dead.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt Jeſus has made ſatisfaction for the Sins of all that are call'd by his Name; and if that ſatisfaction is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly appli'd to all who are true Chriſtians, and Die in the Faith of Chriſt Crucified, and if this is made the abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary Condition of having a Title to that ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I can ſee no ground Wicked Men have to hope for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, if they forfeit that. The Scriptures are altogether ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent as to any thing that can be done for us after Death. To which purpoſe I'll give you the trouble of the following Inſtances,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Holy <hi>David,</hi> when God ſtruck the Child he had by <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> pray'd for its recovery, and faſted and lay all Night upon the Earth: His ſorrow for the Child's Sickneſs was intolerable. But when the Child was Dead, he aroſe from the Earth, and Waſhed, and Anointed himſelf, and changed his Apparel, and came into the Houſe of the Lord and Worſhipped: then he came to his own Houſe, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:56476:36"/> Bread ſet before him he did eat. Then ſaid his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to him, What thing is this that thou haſt done? thou didſt faſt and weep for the Child while it was alive, but when the Child was dead, thou didſt ariſe and eat Bread. And he ſaid, <hi>While the Child was yet alive, I faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and wept:</hi> For I ſaid, <hi>who can tell whether God will be gracious unto me, that the Child may live,</hi> 2 Sam. 12. 22. We read nothing here of any Sacrifice offer'd for the Child, which certainly wou'd have been recorded if ſuch a thing had been done: but he did not ſo much as pray for him or weep after his Death. For,</p>
            <p n="2">2. No Man can by ANY means redeem his Brother, or give to God a ranſom for him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. 7. I think this is plain enough againſt any thing that is pretended to be done for the benefit of the Dead; and if no Ranſom can deem a Man from the State he immediately paſſes into out of this World, what ſignifie the many Maſſes that are ſent up daily for one or other in the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> I think it wou'd not be impertinent to add that of our Saviour, <hi>What ſhall it profit a Man if he ſhall gain the whole World and loſe his own Soul? Or what ſhall a Man give in exchange for his Soul?</hi> Mark 8. 36. Which ſhews the impoſſibility of Redemption from a State after this Life. And this is farther evident in <hi>Luke</hi> 16. in the Diſcourſe between <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Dives,</hi> where <hi>Abraham</hi> tells him, <hi>Verſe</hi> 26. <hi>That between them there is a great Gulf fixed:</hi> So that they which wou'd paſs from one to t'other cou'd not. And then I wou'd fain know how they can ſay that any can be fetch'd out of Purgatory, as Hell is more mildly call'd, to Heaven? But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Apoſtle tells the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 13. <hi>that he wou'd not have 'em to be ignorant, concerning them which are aſleep, nor to ſorrow, as others which have no hope. For if we believe that Jeſus died, and roſe again, even ſo them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus, will God bring with him.</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and the Primitive Chriſtians had their hopes in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:56476:36"/> they had no thought of a ſtate of Puniſhment after Death, from which they were to be freed by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſs, but they built all upon the Merits of Chriſt's Blood, the full ſatisfaction which he had made, and on that ſcore made it their conſtant endeavour to become worthy partakers of it. The Scriptures make no mention of Offertories for the Dead, but in many places they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue clear the contrary: That there is no time or place of calling on God in the Grave, or for thoſe that are in their Graves: All ſhall at the Day of Judgment receive accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what they have done in the Body. There's no Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piation of Guilt after Death, but he that is not abſolv'd in this Life muſt be miſerable for ever. Therefore theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances on the behalf of the Dead, are no better than a breach of the Third Commandment, a taking God's Name in vain, by calling on him for thoſe, for whom he cannot be intreated. Upon the whole therefore, we may truly ſay with the Preacher, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9. 4. <hi>To him that is join'd to all the living, there is hope:</hi> But to him that is dead there is no hope but what his way of living here will admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to him.</p>
            <p>I conclude this with the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 7, &amp;c. <hi>Remember them which have the Rule over you, who have ſpoken unto you the word of God: whoſe Faith follow, conſidering the end of their Converſation. Jeſus Chriſt the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever. Be not carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with divers and ſtrange Doctrines: For it is a good thing that the heart be eſtabliſhed with Grace, not with Meats, which have not profited them which have been occupied therein. We have an Altar whereof they have no right to eat, which ſerve the Tabernacle. For the Bodies of thoſe Beaſts whoſe Blood is brought into the Sanctuary by the High-Prieſt for Sin, are burnt without the Camp. Wherefore Jeſus alſo, that he might ſanctifie the People with his own Blood, ſuffer'd without the Gate. Let us go forth therefore unto him, without the Camp, bearing his reproach. For here we have no continuing
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:56476:37"/> City, but we ſeek one to come. By him therefore let us offer the Sacrifice of Praiſe to God continually, that is, the fruit of our Lips, giving thanks to his Name. But to do good, and to communicate, forget not: for with ſuch Sacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7. Now I come to the Seventh and laſt Enquiry pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, <hi>viz. Whether the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation can be maintain'd by Scripture?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This has been endeavour'd by our Adverſaries, but to no purpoſe. And the Scriptures furniſh us with two very good Arguments to the contrary. Which are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Chriſt's Body can be in but one place at once.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we eat the Body and drink the Blood of Chriſt only by Faith. Againſt both which, Tranſubſtantiation makes Chriſt's Body viſible in a Thouſand places at once; and aſſerts that we eat the very natural Fleſh of Chriſt, and gnaw it with our Teeth as we do our common Meat. And ſince in this Caſe we are denied the uſe of our Senſes, we muſt be judg'd by the Sence of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And firſt, The Scriptures teſtifie, That Chriſt's Body can be in but one place at once.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 11. tells us, <hi>We have the Poor always with us but him we have not always.</hi> For, <hi>John</hi> 16. 28. <hi>As he came forth from the Father into the World, ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain he will leave the World and go to the Father.</hi> Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 19. when he had ſpoken to his Diſciples, <hi>he was received up into Heaven, and ſat on the right hand of God.</hi> And there St. <hi>Stephen</hi> afterwards ſaw him, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 56. In which place, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> teſtifies, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 21. he muſt remain <hi>till the times of the reſtitution of all things.</hi> When, and not before, <hi>he ſhall ſo come in like manner, as he was ſeen to go into Heaven,</hi> Acts 1. 11. Now, I ſuppoſe you know the laſt ſhift they that believe this Doctrine are fain to fly to, is God's Omnipotency, and this they know we dare not contradict. But we know, that though God is able to do any thing, yet 'tis evident in many things he
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:56476:37"/> does not apply his Will to his Ability: And on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, though <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt told the <hi>Jews, Matth.</hi> 3. 9. <hi>That God was able of the Stones of the Earth to raiſe up Children unto</hi> Abraham, we muſt not preſently make the Fable of <hi>Deucalion</hi> and <hi>Pyrrha</hi> an Article of our Faith. For if this wou'd do the bus'neſs, how ſoon wou'd the World be fill'd with Abſurdities, and yet all paſs for Miracles? But if we conſult the Sacred Writings, we ſhall find that though God is ſufficiently declar'd to be Omnipotent, yet he never acted any thing contrary to himſelf, his Power never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd contrary to his Will. Now in the preſent caſe, if we believe the Scriptures to be the Word of God, and that his Will is declar'd in his Word, it ſufficiently appears, that Chriſt muſt be Corporally preſent in Heaven, 'till the end of the World; and then, to ſay that he is Corporally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent on Earth too, and in ſo many Thouſand places at the ſame time, becauſe nothing is impoſſible with God, is to ſay in effect that God, to ſhew his Power, does ſome things which are repugnant to his Will; and to preſerve the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of his Omnipotence inviolate, will upon occaſion contradict his own Word. But the Apoſtles had no ſuch thoughts, ſome of 'em ſaw Chriſt aſcend Bodily into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and others, as St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> afterwards ſaw him Bodily preſent there. Accordingly St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Hebrews, Chap.</hi> 8. <hi>Verſe</hi> 1. that he <hi>is ſet on the Right Hand of the Throne of the Majeſty in the Heavens.</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. <hi>Verſe</hi> 12. <hi>After he had offer'd one Sacrifice for Sins for ever, he ſat down on the Right Hand of God.</hi> Where be pleas'd to obſerve two Errors confuted in one Text, The Sacrifice of the Maſs, in that Chriſt has <hi>offer'd one Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for Sins for ever;</hi> and the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in that after he had offer'd the Sacrifice, <hi>he ſat down on the Right Hand of God.</hi> Therefore his Advice to the <hi>Coloſſians, Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>Verſe</hi> 1. is, <hi>If they are riſen with Chriſt, ſeek thoſe things which are above, where Chriſt ſitteth at the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:56476:38"/> Right Hand of God. For,</hi> Phil. 3. 20. <hi>our Converſation,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is in Heaven, from whence alſo we look for the Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Wherefore, <hi>Madam,</hi> I think the Counſel of our Lord himſelf is beſt to be follow'd, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 23. <hi>If any Man ſhall ſay unto you, Lo, here is Chriſt, or there, believe it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Another Argument deducible from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, againſt this Doctrine, I told you, was, <hi>That we eat the Body, and drink the Blood of Chriſt, only by Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>John 6. 47, <hi>&amp;c. Verily, verily I ſay unto you, he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth on me hath Everlaſting Life. I am that Bread of Life. Your Fathers did eat Manna in the Wilderneſs, and are dead. This is the Bread which cometh down from Heaven, that a Man may eat thereof, and not die. I am the Living Bread which came down from Heaven. If any Man eat of this Bread, he ſhall live for ever: And the Bread that I will give, is my Fleſh, which I will give for the Life of the World.</hi> Where we are to conſider, Firſt, That Faith in Chriſt is made the Condition of having Everlaſting Life, <hi>Verſe</hi> 47. Secondly, The Bread of Life, which, <hi>Verſe</hi> 51. is call'd his Fleſh, is only that Spiritual Nouriſhment of the Soul, which comes by that Faith in Chriſt: And therefore he ſays, that <hi>if any Man eat of this Bread, he ſhall live for ever.</hi> Whence I think it plainly appears, that eating Chriſt's Fleſh, and believing on him, are only terms uſed promiſcuouſly one for t'other, and ſo make nothing at all for Tranſubſtantiation. But the chief of the Argument is to come, <hi>Verſe</hi> 52, &amp;c.—<hi>The</hi> Jews <hi>therefore ſtrove among themſelves, ſaying, How can this Man give us his Fleſh to eat? Then Jeſus ſaid unto them, Verily verily I ſay unto you, Except ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his Blood, ye have no Life in you. Whoſo eateth my Fleſh, and Drinketh my Blood, hath Eternal Life, and I will raiſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:56476:38"/> him up at the laſt Day. For my Fleſh is Meat indeed, and my Blood is Drink indeed. He that eateth my Fleſh, and drinketh my Blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him. As the Living Father hath ſent me, and I live by the Father: ſo, he that eateth me, even he ſhall live by me. This is that Bread which came down from Heaven; not as your Fathers did eat Manna, and are dead: He that eateth of this Bread ſhall live for ever.</hi>—Perhaps you may think, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> that theſe reiterated expreſſions are Indications plain enough that our Saviour here intends Tranſubſtantiation: But I aſſure you they mean nothing leſs. For, firſt, he ſays, <hi>Except ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his Blood, ye have no Life in you.</hi> And on the contrary, <hi>Whoſo eateth his Fleſh, and drinketh his Blood, hath Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, and he will raiſe him up at the laſt Day.</hi> Now, if our Saviour ſpeaks all this of his natural Fleſh and Blood, with which he was cloathed, and which was nail'd to the Croſs and ſplit on the Ground; and laſtly, which he carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him into Heaven; and if, according to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, his natural Fleſh and Blood are as really eaten and drunk in the Lord's Supper, Then, all Men, bad as well as good, nay any living Creature that is but capable of eating and drinking, may be in as fair a way to Heaven as the devouteſt Profeſſor of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity. For if eating the Fleſh of Chriſt will carry one to Heaven, give a Dog a piece of the Tranſubſtantiated Bread, and why may not he by eating it go thither too? However, to ſeclude Beaſts, it wou'd be a bleſſed World certainly, if the worſt of Men were in as ſure a way to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, as the beſt! which muſt be, if the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, and our Saviour's Words hold together. For he ſays, his <hi>Fleſh is Meat indeed, and</hi> his <hi>Blood is Drink indeed.</hi> And Tranſubſtantiation gives all Men the real Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt, and by eating and drinking them we get Salvation, which is here call'd Eternal Life. But
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:56476:39"/> Secondly, <hi>He that eateth Chriſt's Fleſh, and drinketh his Blood, dwelleth in Chriſt, and Chriſt in him.</hi> Now can Chriſt dwell in a Wicked Man, or Unbeliever: <hi>What fellowſhip hath Chriſt with Belial?</hi> Thirdly, <hi>This is that Bread which came down from Heaven: not as our Fathers did eat Manna, and are dead: he that eateth of this Bread ſhall live for ever:</hi> Whence obſerve, If one thing is to be underſtood according to the Letter, another is alſo. And then if the Letter intends Tranſubſtantiation, according to the Letter likewiſe, they who eat the Fleſh of Chriſt preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Immortal. And thus the <hi>Jews</hi> underſtood our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, when they cried out, <hi>Lord, evermore give us of this Bread,</hi> Verſe 34. But 'tis appointed for all Men once to die. Therefore, eating the Fleſh of Chriſt, and drinking his Blood, can mean nothing but our feeding on him by Faith unto Salvation. And, if by eating the Fleſh of Chriſt, and drinking his Blood, we ſhall live for ever, and yet no Man can be ſaved unleſs he believes in him, either our Saviour muſt be thought to contradict himſelf, or elſe this overthrows the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, and proves that we only eat and drink the Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt by Faith. And I appeal to your ſelf, <hi>Madam,</hi> to judge which of the two 'tis moſt reaſonable to believe. But that what our Saviour ſays here, is not to be underſtood according to the Letter, will appear if we purſue it a little farther, <hi>Verſe</hi> 60.—<hi>Many therefore of his Diſciples, when they heard this, ſaid, This is a hard Saying, who can hear it? When Jeſus knew in himſelf, that his Diſciples murmured at it, he ſaid unto them, Doth this offend you? What and if ye ſhall ſee the Son of Man aſcend up where he was before? It is the Spirit that quickeneth, the Fleſh profiteth nothing: the words that I ſpeak unto you, they are Spirit, and they are Life. But there are ſome of you that believe not.</hi> From all which, I cou'd tell you, <hi>Madam,</hi> and upon good ground too, that there is nothing in this Chapter, or very little at
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:56476:39"/> moſt, touching the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> but all that our Saviour ſays concerning his Fleſh and Blood, is to be underſtood of his exemplary Life, and wholſome Doctrine, which is Meat and Drink indeed. But ſuppoſing the whole diſcourſe to be upon that ſubject, yet there can be nothing of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation contain'd in it. Which will yet more fully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by conſidering how often he urges the neceſſity of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving on him in order to Salvation: <hi>Verſe</hi> 29. <hi>This,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is the work of God, that ye believe on him whom he hath ſent.</hi> So, <hi>Verſe</hi> 35. <hi>He that believeth on me, ſhall never thirſt. But I ſaid unto you, that ye alſo have ſeen me, and believe not.</hi> Again, <hi>Verſe</hi> 40. <hi>And this is the will of him that ſent me, that every one which ſeeth the Son, and believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on him, may have Everlaſting Life: and I will raiſe him up at the laſt Day.</hi> So likewiſe, <hi>Verſe</hi> 47. <hi>He that believeth on me, hath Everlaſting Life.</hi> And this believing on him, in other places of the Chapter he calls, coming to him; as, <hi>Verſe</hi> 35, 37, 44, 45. And in other places again, it is call'd eating his Fleſh, and drinking his Blood. Whence 'tis evident, they are all Synonymous terms uſed to expreſs one and the ſame thing. But to proceed.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 1. tells us, that <hi>all our Fathers were under the Cloud, and all paſſed through the Sea: and were all baptized unto</hi> Moſes <hi>in the Cloud, and in the Sea, and did all eat the ſame ſpiritual Meat, and did all drink the ſame ſpiritual Drink (for they drank of that ſpiritual Rock that followed them: and that Rock was Chriſt).</hi> Now the Paſchal Lamb, was as lively a repreſentation of Chriſt, the Lamb ſlain from the Foundation of the World, as our Bread and Wine are, of the breaking his Body and ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Blood upon the Croſs: yet 'twas never thought that they in the Paſſover did eat and drink Chriſt's real Fleſh and Blood; but only in that Feaſt they fed on him by Faith. And ſo when we come duly prepar'd to the Lord's
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:56476:40"/> Table, we are Partakers of his Body and Blood by Faith, by which alſo Chriſt dwelleth in our hearts, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 17. Our Saviour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 5. ſays, <hi>I am the Vine, ye are the Branches: he that abideth in me, and I in him, the ſame bringeth forth much fruit: for without me ye can do nothing.</hi> Now, if all our Saviour's words muſt be taken according to the letter, which muſt we rather believe, that his Fleſh is Bread, to be eaten by us as we do our ordinary Food, or that he is a great Tree, and we Chriſtians are ſo many Branches growing from him; or that we are mere Sheep feeding on a Common, and he the Shepherd to look after us; or laſtly, that he is a Door hung upon Hinges, thro' which we Sheep muſt enter into our Paſture? I wou'd fain know, if all theſe were to be taken literally, what we ſhou'd do to know which was true, and which not? Such Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions as theſe muſt be taken Metaphorically; and ſo, As we uſually enter into a Houſe by the Door, ſo we go to Heaven by Chriſt: As a Shepherd takes care that none of his Sheep go aſtray, ſo Chriſt the good Shepherd of our Souls, will loſe none of all them that are his: As a Vine gives Nouriſhment to its Branches, ſo is Chriſt a Vine to us, by whom we live and grow ripe for a joyful Harveſt, or Vintage: And laſtly, as Bread is eaten to ſuſtain this Temporal Life; ſo Chriſt is that Spiritual Food on which we feed by Faith unto life Everlaſting.</p>
            <p>To what has been ſaid on this Subject, we may add ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Texts of Scripture, which aſſert the Elements which are the Matter of this Feaſt, to be the ſame after Conſecration, as they were before. Thus the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 16, <hi>The cup of Bleſſing which we bleſs, is it not the Communion of the Blood of Chriſt? The Bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the Body of Chriſt?</hi> So again, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 26, <hi>As often as ye eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, ye do ſhew the Lord's death till he come.</hi> But that which is chiefly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:56476:40"/> on, is what our Lord himſelf ſaid at the Inſtitution of his Supper; <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 26. <hi>And as they were eating, Jeſus took Bread, and bleſſed it, and brake it, and gave it to the Diſciples, and ſaid, Take, eat, this is my Body. And he took the Cup, and gave thanks, and gave it to them, ſaying, drink ye all of it. For this is my Blood of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is ſhed for many for the Remiſſion of Sins.</hi> If here is not plain Tranſubſtantiation, I know not where to find it. Our Saviour himſelf in the preſence of his Diſciples takes a piece of Bread, and plainly affirms that 'tis his Body; and ſhall not we believe him? yes, ſurely. But what follows? <hi>Verſ.</hi> 29, <hi>But I ſay unto you, I will not drink henceforth of this Fruit of the Vine, until that day when I drink it new with you in my Father's Kingdom.</hi> I think he tells us as plainly here, that the Wine was ſtill the Fruit of the Vine after Conſecration, as before he did, that it was his Blood. But to this we may add what St. <hi>Luke</hi> ſays of his inſtituting his Supper, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 19, <hi>And he took Bread, and gave thanks, and brake it, and gave unto them, ſaying, This is my Body which is given for you:</hi> and ſo of the Cup, <hi>This is the New Teſtament of my Blood, which is ſhed for you.</hi> Where, if I were given to Criticiſm, I might take notice, as <hi>Beza</hi> has done, that Chriſt ſays, <hi>This is my Body, which is given, for you,</hi> not <hi>to you.</hi> But to let that paſs; we know that Chriſt was not yet Crucified, till after the inſtitution of this Feaſt: So that here's another figure, he makes uſe of the Preſent Tenſe inſtead of the Future, inſtead of, <hi>this is my Body, which ſhall be given for you,</hi> he ſays, <hi>which is given for you,</hi> as if it was a thing already done. Now in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, it wou'd have been much more for Tranſubſtantiation, if he had us'd the Future Tenſe, and told 'em plainly, <hi>This is my Body which ſhall be crucified for you:</hi> and his acting the contrary, nulls all Pretences to the Doctrine from his words. But <hi>Bellarmin</hi> has wittily ſuggeſted another kind of Argument, which I ſhall the rather mention, becauſe it
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:56476:41"/> has lately been ſtarted afreſh, and that is, <q>If theſe words, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> do not intend Tranſubſtantiation, they muſt want a Grammatical Conſtruction. For the Pronoun <hi>Hoc</hi> cannot Adjectively agree with <hi>Bread,</hi> as its antecedent Subſtantive: for <hi>Bread</hi> is of the Maſculine Gender. Neither can <hi>Hoc</hi> be ſpoken Subſtantively, of a thing that is ſeen and openly known, unleſs that thing be of the Neuter Gender: But <hi>Bread</hi> is of the Maſculine, both in the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin.</hi> No man going to ſhew another his Brother wou'd ſay, <hi>Hoc eſt frater meus:</hi> neither wou'd any man ſay of the King's Image, <hi>Hoc eſt</hi> Caeſar.</q> But all this is but a ſly Inſinuation, to cajole thoſe that know no more of Grammar than this Argument wou'd teach 'em. And I have ſo much Charity for that great Man, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him too good a Grammarian to be gull'd by ſo poor an Artifice. I ſuppoſe he cou'd not be ignorant, if he knew any thing almoſt of the invalidity of ſuch a ſhift, he knew well enough, I dare ſay, that <hi>Hoc</hi> is here us'd as a Relative, and, as ſuch, that it might very well refer to either of the two Subſtantives, <hi>Bread,</hi> or <hi>Body;</hi> and in this caſe the ſeeing, or not ſeeing the Bread ſignified nothing: but as the Relative wou'd refer to both <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Body,</hi> it was in his Power to make it agree with which of the Subſtantives pleas'd him. And ſo, <hi>Hic eſt Corpus meum,</hi> wou'd have made as much for Tranſubſtantiation, as <hi>Hoc,</hi> &amp;c. and wou'd have been as liable to Cavil and Diſpute: yet he that ſpake the words wou'd ſhew himſelf a good Grammarian either way. And ſo, tho' 'tis true, 'twou'd be improper to ſay of a man's Brother, <hi>Hoc eſt frater meus,</hi> yet it may well enough be ſaid of the King's Image, <hi>Hoc eſt</hi> Caeſar, becauſe, as <hi>Hoc</hi> relates to the Image and not to <hi>Caeſar</hi> immediately, the Image being a thing without life, for that reaſon the Relative is of the Neuter Gender. But to take a Simile nearer to the preſent queſtion: Suppoſe a little Girl, as like her Father as tis poſſible for her to be, ſhe being among
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:56476:41"/> more of her Siſters, any Perſon ſhou'd ſingle her out from the reſt, and ſay of her, <hi>This is the Father him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;</hi> I wou'd know how we ſhou'd make this Sentence into <hi>Latin</hi> to avoid a Metamorphoſis? I muſt confeſs, if it had been ſpoken thus, <hi>This Girl,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hoec Puella,</hi> the Article of the Feminine Gender had been moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: but as the word <hi>Girl</hi> is only included for under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and <hi>Father</hi> expreſt, the Article of the Maſculine Gender is as proper, becauſe, the Article may indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently be referr'd to either the <hi>Girl,</hi> or the <hi>Father.</hi> And this ſuggeſts to me another Argument againſt taking theſe words of our Saviour literally. The Girl here, by reaſon of her being ſo like her Father, is ſaid to be the very Father himſelf: Now wou'd not the By-ſtanders be call'd Fools or worſe, if they ſhou'd preſently vindicate the Poet's Metamorphoſis of <hi>Iphis,</hi> by believing the Girl is at that inſtant turn'd into a Man? and yet the Expreſſion is no Hyperbole; but as the common way of ſpeech is, to call the Picture or Repreſentative of a Man, the Man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: and thus our Saviour might ſay, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> and yet only intend the ſign for the thing ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified.</p>
            <p>All this while, I think I have not made the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to our Sences, tho' in a Matter ſo obvious to 'em, and yet can find no ground for the belief of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation. But, as in things that are obvious to ſence, our Senſes cannot be deceiv'd; ſo neither did our Saviour ever deny us the Evidence of our Senſes in ſuch caſes: but thus he expoſtulates; <hi>Have ye not ſeen the Miracles which I did openly?</hi> And in order to convince us of the reallity of his Reſurrection, he appeals con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to our Senſes: <hi>Reach hither thine hand, and thruſt it into my ſide; a Spirit hath not fleſh and bones,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:56476:42"/> as ye ſee me have: He is not here,</hi> ſays the Angel, <hi>but is riſen as he ſaid; ſee the place where they laid him, There's none of him.</hi> And why might not he have had two Bodies then, one in the Grave, and another to ſhew to his Diſciples, as well as ſo many Thouſand now? No, then his Reſurrection wou'd have been taken as a Trick, that ſome body like him had perſonated him: for 'twou'd be contrary to ſence, that the ſame Body ſhou'd be whole and entire in two places ſo far diſtant at the ſame time. 'Twou'd be a Miracle, but againſt reaſon; and that no Miracle ever was, but the Miracle of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation. Some Articles of Faith, are above our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Sence; but none contrary to both Reaſon and Sence.</p>
            <p>And thus, Madam, I have endeavour'd to prove the great Diſagreement between ſome of the Principal Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And this I preſume I may ſay for my ſelf, that wherein I have meddl'd in the clearing of an obſcure Text, I have done nothing out of a deſign'd Endeavour to run down an Opinion, but as I thought in my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence it was Erroneous.</p>
            <p>One thing only I deſire at your hands, if you let any of the adverſe Party have a ſight of theſe Papers, that you wou'd deſire 'em to be upon the ſquare, and not quote Humane Teſtimonies againſt the Holy Scriptures: And if they can make good thoſe Doctrines here cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd, from the Word of God, notwithſtanding what is here produc'd, I my ſelf will become a Roman Catholick with the firſt appearance of Truth in thoſe Doctrines I have hitherto thought Falſe. But as I think that can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be done, ſo I humbly recommend this plain, but, I hope, faithful Piece to your ſerious Peruſal, and hope it
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:56476:42"/> may prove to your compleat Satisfaction, and that you may reap the full Benefit of a ſincere Believer of the Goſpel in the end. Which, that God of his infinite Grace and Mercy, through his Son Chriſt Jeſus, will grant to you and yours, is, and ever ſhall be the conſtant and hearty Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
